<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The importunate begger for things necessary, or necessity, without deniall Or a treatise, wherein is shewed the lawfullnesse of praying absolutely for necessary temporall things, without doubting or wavering, and that the saints of God may and ought, as absolutely depend upon God, for their dayly bread, as they may for the pardon of their sinnes, and that the cause is in themselves, who doe not obtaine them. Whereunto is annexed an answer to Mr. Norrice his 5 arguments, which were framed against it, together with an answer to his Prosopopeia, wherein, as well the insufficiency of those arguments, as the deceitfullnesse of his collections, is plainely manifested by R.B.</title>
            <author>Boye, Rice.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842528</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The importunate begger for things necessary, or necessity, without deniall Or a treatise, wherein is shewed the lawfullnesse of praying absolutely for necessary temporall things, without doubting or wavering, and that the saints of God may and ought, as absolutely depend upon God, for their dayly bread, as they may for the pardon of their sinnes, and that the cause is in themselves, who doe not obtaine them. Whereunto is annexed an answer to Mr. Norrice his 5 arguments, which were framed against it, together with an answer to his Prosopopeia, wherein, as well the insufficiency of those arguments, as the deceitfullnesse of his collections, is plainely manifested by R.B.</title>
                  <author>Boye, Rice.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J.F. Stam],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare 1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.B. = Rice Boye.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norris, Edward, 1584-1659 --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7192:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IMPORTVNATE BEGGER For things neceſſary, or neceſſity, without deniall.</p>
            <p>Or a Treatiſe, wherein is ſhewed the lawfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of praying abſolutely for neceſſary temporall things, without doubting or wavering, and that the Saints of God may and ought, as abſolutely depend upon God, for their dayly bread, as they may for the pardon of their ſinnes, and that the cauſe is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed</hi> An Anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. NORRICE his 5 Arguments, which were framed againſt it, together with an Anſwer to his Proſopopeia, wherein, as well the inſufficiency of thoſe Arguments, as the deceitfullneſſe of his Collections, is plainely manifeſted <hi>By</hi> R. B.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Cast thy burthen upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſteine thee: He ſhall never ſuffer the Righteous to be mooved,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 55.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Ieſus ſaid unto him, if thou canst beleeve, all things are poſſible to him that beleeveth,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Mark. 9.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7192:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7192:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> The well-affected Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I firſt conceaved and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Treatiſe (gentle Reader) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning praying for temporall bleſſings, it was farre from my thoughts, that ever it ſhould come abroad to the publike view of the world: it being (as it were) but a Letter ſent to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> in private, wherein (by his ſpeciall intreatie) I unfolded myſelf unto him, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſubject before ſpecified, as allſo what I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his 5 Arguments intentively framed by him, to croſſe or contradict what I before affirmed to him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, concerning the point of <hi>praying abſolutely for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neceſſaryes.</hi> I ſay, I did not once imagine, that this which I thus wrote to a freind in private, ſhould ever have bene printed and made publike. That which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioneth me now (contrary to my former thoughts) to commit it in a publike manner to every mans eye and cenſure, is <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> his ſlanderous miſconſtructions and falſe reports of my writings, which he cauſed long ſince (about 5 yeares) to fly up and downe the Country: And now (fearing belike they were forgotten) they are againe renued and revived by him. For no ſooner had I
<pb facs="tcp:7192:3"/>ſent him in writing (according as hee deſired me) what I conceived of the point above named, together with an anſwer to his 5 Arguments, but preſently hee gave out (and that in writing) that my writings contained in them divers errours and abſurdities, if not blaſphemyes, as in my anſwer to his Proſopopeia is fully manifeſted.</p>
            <p>Thoſe falſe reports and injurious ſlanders being (as I ſuppoſe) allmoſt forgotten, are againe renued by him, and now on foote as freſh as ever: by reaſon whereof I undergoe many heavy cenſures, which to me is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding grievous, both in reſpect of the inward and outward man: for as the ſoule is wounded, ſo a mans good name by ſuch dealing is ſtained. Wherefore I could not chuſe, but commit it to the view of all, chooſing rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf and writings, to the various cenſures of the multitude, then that the truth (through my ſilence) ſhould be ſmothered by the foggy miſts of falſhood, and the leaſt occaſion given for any one to thinke, that thoſe ſcandalls, which are falſly layd upon me, are but juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved blame.</p>
            <p>I have no liberty to add too, or dimuniſh any thing from the firſt coppy, but as I wrote it to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice,</hi> and as he hath it coppyed in his hands, ſo I am compelled to publiſh it; and that for 2 reaſons. Firſt leſt hee ſhould ſay and affirme, that theſe are not the writings which hee had from me, and ſo free himſelf (at leaſt as ſome may take it) from ſome (if not from all) of that deſerved blame, which is layd upon him, for abuſing my writings. And ſecondly that his ſlanderous collections and aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions caſt upon me, in reſpect of my writings, may be plainly ſeene by them that read my writings, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with his ſpeeches, together with his colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions hereafter mentioned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7192:3"/>
            <p> Now ſeeing there is a neceſſity layd upon me (as thou ſeeſt curteous and well-diſpoſed Reader) to publiſh theſe my writings without correction, either of matter or words, I would intreate thee to deale with me, as (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume) thou (being in the ſame caſe with me) wouldeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire others to deale with thee, even charitably to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue all things, and interpret them in the better part. Looke not ſo much (it being written to a freind in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate) for curiouſly compoſed ſentences, and elegancie of phraſe, as upon the truth of the matter, and the comfort which the right imbracing of the ſame, will bring unto thy ſoule; for it will not onely uphold thee as an ancre in the midſt of the foming waves of this worlds calamities, but allſo free thee from innumerable inconveniences, which otherwiſe are like to befall thee.</p>
            <p>If upon thy peruſing my writings, thou findeſt any ſuch errours of matter as are reported of me, and canſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt them unto me as my ſinne, I ſhall willingly confeſſe my fayling, and give publike ſatisfaction. I need ſay no more for preſent, in regard I have given thee ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements in the Epilogue or Concluſion of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe: onely I deſire thee to take due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as well of thoſe advertiſements, as allſo of thoſe other truths, contained in theſe few ſheets, and weigh them all in the balance of the Sanctuary, and not (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy prejudicate opinion of the Author) to deprive thy ſelf of thoſe priviledges, which the right imbracing of thoſe truths, hereafter manifeſted, will bring unto thee. Howſoever my hearts deſire and prayer to God is, that the truth may ſtill flouriſh, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the many ſubtill deluſions of the adverſaries, who with their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning arguments, doe like Iannes and Iambres, thoſe Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian juglers, ſecretly reſiſt the truth: yea my deſire is,
<pb facs="tcp:7192:4"/>that it may evidently and with ſpeed appeare, that the Truth hath devoured errour, as the ſerpent of Moſes did the Enchanters: Thus (aſſuredly exſpecting Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of my deſire) I commit what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to thy conſideration, and thee to Gods protection, wiſhing thee to uſe what I have written to thy comfort, praying the Lord withall, to make thy heart ſtable and unblamable in holineſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all good affection</hi> RICE BOYE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7192:4"/>
            <head>For praying abſolutely for neceſſary temporall things, without doubting and wavering, and that the Saints of God may and ought, as abſolutely depend upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, for their dayly bread, as they may for the pardon of their ſinnes, and that the cauſe is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be thought of many, that concerning prayer for outward things, wee doe but (as the ſaying is) <hi>nodum in ſcirpo quaerere,</hi> even contend about trifles. Indeed the matter of our contention (at the firſt ſight) doth not ſeeme great, but being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, it is of great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence; <hi>It is for the faith,</hi> for which we are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>earnestly to contend.</hi> That which is the ground of this controverſy, is this word, <hi>If,</hi> which ſome doe labour to joyne with, and wee labour to ſeperate, and remoove it from the prayers of Gods faithfull ſervants. Here then is the ſumme of the whole matter. They affirme that for outward neceſſary things, wee ought to pray with an, If; but we affirme that, If, in all ſuch prayers muſt be layd aſide. Wherefore it ſhall not be unmeete (before we ſpeake particularly of the matter in hand) to ſhew how this word, <hi>If,</hi> is taken in the Scriptures. This <hi>particle, If,</hi> then is taken in the Scriptures either for a terme of <hi>condition,</hi> or els for a terme of <hi>doubt.</hi> It is a terme of <hi>condition</hi> Deut. 4.30.31. <hi>If thou turne to the Lord thy God, and ſhall be obedient unto his voyce: he will not forſake thee,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7192:5"/>neither destroy thee, &amp;c.</hi> This and all other ſuch like places, may be turned <hi>participially,</hi> thus: Thou turning to the Lord, and being obedient unto him, he will not forſake thee, nor deſtroy thee. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly this <hi>particle, If,</hi> is not onely a terme of <hi>condition,</hi> but alſo a terme of <hi>doubt,</hi> and diſtruſtfullneſſe; and ſo it is 2. Kings 7.19. <hi>If the Lord ſhould make windowes in heaven, might ſuch things be?</hi> As if he had ſayd, I cannot beleeve that ſuch a plenty of corne will be in Samariah, notwithſtanding the Lord doth make windowes in heaven. He doubted of the truth of the Prophets word: Now to the thing in hand. In what ſence then is this word <hi>(If)</hi> uſed in prayer for neceſſary temporall <hi>bleſſings?</hi> as it is <hi>conditionall</hi> or doubtfull? if conditionall (as the truth is, the moſt would have it) then our prayers for outward neceſſary bleſſings muſt be framed thus; <hi>Oh Father, if the gift of things neceſsary for my preſent being ſhall ſtand with thy will, then be pleaſed to beſtow it upon me.</hi> In which petition this word (If) is not onely conditionall, but alſo doubtfull: We doe not by this ſaying referre it to the will of God; but in ſo praying we doubt whether it doth agree with the will of God, to beſtow upon us things neceſſary for our preſent being, which maner of praying doth manifeſt both <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>infidelity;</hi> wee know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the will of God or not, to give us ſuch things as we aſke, and then no marvaill, if we doubt whether we ſhall have them yea or no. Therefore contrary to the common opinion we conclude, <hi>That the particle (If) ought to be excluded from the prayers of Gods faithfull ſervants, yea from ſuch prayers which they make for outward neceſſary bleſſings.</hi> This doth appeare by our Saviours words Mat. 6. where he commaundeth his Diſciples to pray for things neceſſary, for ſoule and body, without any If at all. I thinke it be receaved of all without contradiction as a generall truth, that that prayer, which we call the Lords prayer, (and ſo call it becauſe it is the Lord Chriſts owne framing) is <hi>exemplar abſolutiſſimum,</hi> ſuch an abſolute patterne of prayer, as that, there is nothing in it ſuperfluous, neither is there any thing eſſentiall to prayer wanting. If then nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſuperfluous, neither yet any thing eſſentiall to prayer wanting, then ſurely this particle, If, ought to be excluded from all the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Lords prayer, becauſe we find that in the whole forme it is wanting. You all acknowledge that there is no need of any (If) in any of the petitions, but in the fourth onely, in which petition ye
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7192:5"/>ſay that it is <hi>implied.</hi> If this be graunted, then it muſt needs be, firſt that ſomewhat eſſentiall to prayer in Chriſts forme is wanting, and then ſecondly that Chriſts forme is not perfect (which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to your owne tenent) for ye confeſſe that the forme is perfect, and then it muſt needs be (if the forme be not perfect) that there wanted either ſkill or will in Chriſt to make ſuch a forme of prayer, which could not be mended, which for any man to affirme, is no leſſe then blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (for ought I ſee) ſo long as wee keepe our ſelves cloſe to the word of God, and frame our petitions according to his will revealed in the ſame, there is no need of any (If) in any of our prayers, no not in ſuch prayers which wee make unto God for temporall bleſſings. But more of this hereafter. Now more fully to manifeſt, and more evidently to proove our tenent, concerning ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute prayer for temporall neceſſary bleſſings, wee will draw all the matter (as is ſpecified in our title afore-mentioned) into theſe three heads. <hi>First that neceſſarie temporall bleſſings, ought to be prayed for without doubting or wavering. Or thus: Faith without doubting is as well required in ſuch prayers, which are made to God for neceſsarie temporall things, as it is in thoſe which are made for ſpirituall bleſſings. Secondly, that the Saints of God may and ought, as abſolutelie depend upon the promiſes of God, for their daily bread, (.i.) for things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsarie, as they may for the pardon of their ſinnes. And thirdly, that the cauſe is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine them.</hi> Theſe are the branches, which (as I conceive) doe naturally ſpring from the roote of our tenent, concerning abſolute prayer for neceſſary temporall things, what fruit doe grow upon each of them, ye ſhall (by Gods aſſiſtance) plainely and briefly ſee: And firſt of the firſt; namely, <hi>That neceſsarie temporall things ought to be prayed for, without doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and wavering.</hi> That faith without wavering is required in all prayers made unto God, as well for temporall as ſpirituall things, I thinke it is not (I know it cannot be) denyed of any. For faith in prayer is not accidentall, but eſſentiall, it is not contingent, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, it cannot be ſeperated from prayer, <hi>ſine ſubjecti interitu,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its violation. Faith is that which makes prayer to be as a ſweete ſmelling ſacrifice in Gods noſtrills, but without it, it is diſpleaſing: <hi>For whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14. laſt. Whereupon Auguſtine affirmeth, that our <hi>righteouſneſſe is diſcerned from unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7192:6"/>not by the law of works, but of faith, without which faith, whatſoever ſeemed good works, are ſinnes, and turned into ſinnes; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be that ſuch prayers will bring either comfort to man, or glory to God, ſeeing they doe not pleaſe him, whom to pleaſe without faith</hi> (as the Apoſtle affirmeth Heb. 11.6.) <hi>is impoſſible.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon our Apoſtle Paul doth expreſly commaund us, to ſend faith with all our prayers, as appeareth 1. Tim. 2.8. <hi>I will therefore</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands without wrath and doubting.</hi> And if any man ſhould thinke, the Apoſtles meaning in this place is reſtrained onely to ſpirituall things, our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall give him ſatisfaction Luk. 12.28.29. where he doeth ſpeake of temporalls, from whom our Apoſtle did fetch his text, where he doeth reproove the Diſciples for their <hi>infidelity,</hi> concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, and he doeth draw reprooving arguments from the leſſe to the greater; did the Lord <hi>feed the fowles, and cloath the graſſe? how much more will he feed and cloath you, oh ye of little faith?</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he addeth this prohibition, <hi>Seeke not what ye ſhall eate, or what ye ſhall drinke, neither be ye of doubtfull mind.</hi> Hence it is that our Apoſtle Iames doeth lay downe a rule how to pray, <hi>But let him aſke in faith nothing wavering,</hi> Iames 1.6. In which words are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Apoſtle as a ſinne, all wavering &amp; doubting prayers, which he doeth proove in the inſuing words by three ſeverall things. The firſt is by a ſimilitude, he that <hi>wavereth and doubteth in prayer, is like a wave in the ſea driven with the wind and toſsed,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they pleaſe not God. Secondly he prooveth it by a reaſon drawen from the diſcommodity, which it bringeth; It doeth hinder a man from the obtaining the thing he deſireth. Thirdly hee doeth condemne it by a generall ſentence, received as true of all men: <hi>A wavering minded man is unſtable in all his wayes.</hi> Thus it is plaine, that wavering and doubting in prayer, is by the holy Ghoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as a ſinne, and the contrary, namely, ſolide, certaine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted confidence required. And ſurely concerning the thing in hand, we may ſay with a Domeſticke writer, <hi>If faith be a vertue, then doubting is a vice:</hi> for certainly (as we ſayd before) it is unreſiſtable, <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne.</hi> Adde unto all this the definitions of prayer, as we find them recorded by our owne Divines. By ſome it is defined thus: <hi>To make prayer, is to put up requeſt to God, according to his word, from a contrite heart in the name of Chriſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7192:6"/>with full aſſurance to be heard.</hi> This laſt clauſe (ſaith the Author) is ſo neceſſary in prayer, as that the want of it maketh prayer no prayer; for (ſaith hee) <hi>how can a man pray for any thing effectuallie, who doubteth whether he ſhall obtaine it or no.</hi> Whereupon hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, <hi>that prayer must be made with faith, whereby a man must have certaine aſſurance to be heard.</hi> By others it is defined thus: Prayer is an ardent affection, tending unto God, whereby wee aſke and looke for, onely from God in Chriſt, things belonging to ſoule and body, <hi>Secundum ipſius mandatum &amp; promiſſiones,</hi> according to that which he hath commaunded to aſke, and promiſed to give. Againe Calvine doeth define it thus: <hi>Est enim quaedam hominum cum Deo communicatio, &amp;c.</hi> It is a certaine communication, or tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of men with God, whereby they entring the heavenly San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, they doe ſpeake or mention unto him (as it were face to face) his promiſes, and that they beleeve, that whatſoever the word doeth warrant unto them, <hi>non fuiſse vanum,</hi> it cannot be in vaine. All theſe definitions tend to one and the ſame purpoſe, in them all the point is verified: That faith without wavering is neceſſary requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all prayer, as well for temporall, as ſpirituall bleſſings. And to what end (ſayth Calvine) doeth our Saviour ſo often ſay to the diſeaſed, according to thy faith be it unto thee? but to manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, <hi>quod citra fidem nihil conſequi nos poſſe,</hi> that without faith we cannot, nor may not exſpect to receive any thing at the hands of God. And ſurely if our prayers are not grounded upon faith, tis but a vaine thing once to thinke that they will profit. Wherefore (good Chriſtian Reader) I beſeech thee in the bowels of mercy in Chriſt Ieſus, ponder well and conſider this, ground thy prayer upon faith, and thy faith upon Gods Word, aſke what thou doeſt aſke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his revealed will, walke within thy limits, keepe faith and a good conſcience, wreſtle with God (as did Iacob Gen. 32.) and then feare not to call thy ſelf by <hi>the name of Iſrael; for as a Prince ſhalt thou have power with God, and with men, and ſhalt prevaile.</hi> Call not Gods power into queſtion, doubt not of his willingneſſe to ſuccour thee, neither ſtagger at any of his promiſes, no not at thoſe which he hath made unto thee for thy dayly maintenance, for ſurely they are all faithfull, thou mayeſt abſolutely without all doubt depend upon them, which is our ſecond branch, and the reaſon of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7192:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>That the Saints of God may and ought, as abſolutelie depend upon, the promiſes of God, for their daily bread, (.i.) for things neceſsarie, as they may for the pardon of their ſinnes,</hi> is alſo eaſily juſtifiable by the Scriptures. It is indifferently acknowledged by our whole Church, that the promiſes of God, concerning the pardon of ſinnes, and life eternall, ought abſolutely to be depended upon God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſcruple. What? ſhall the promiſes, concerning the ſoule, (which is the greater) be relied upon and beleeved? and ſhall the truth of the promiſes, concerning the body, (which is the leſſe) be ſuſpected? <hi>If I have told you earthlie things</hi> (ſayth Chriſt Ioh. 3.12.) <hi>&amp; ye beleeve me not, how ſhall ye beleeve if I tell you heavenlie things?</hi> If wee dare not give credit to the leſſe, how ſhall wee beleeve the greater? for our faith hath all one ground. The ground of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon God, for ſoule or body, is his promiſes, which God in Chriſt abſolutely made to all his ſervants, as the Apoſtle prooveth 2. Cor. 1.10. <hi>All the promiſes</hi> (as well temporaries as ſpiritualls) <hi>are in Christ Yea, and in him Amen.</hi> Hee is faithfull in every one of them, yea for the keeping of the leaſt, he hath layd his credit to pawne, and if God failes in any of his promiſes, his credit muſt needs ſuffer. But our Apoſtle hath remooued this doubt Heb. 10.23. <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis Dominus,</hi> the Lord is faithfull that promiſeth. And upon this foundation (as I ſayd before) is our faith and confident depending upon God, grounded. He hath promiſed to ſave me Mal. 3.16. <hi>They ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Hee hath promiſed never to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, nor to leave me, Ioſuah 1.5. <hi>I will not leave thee, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee.</hi> Hee hath promiſed to comfort me in diſtreſſe, Pſal. 91.15. <hi>I will be with him in trouble;</hi> Hee hath promiſed to give me things neceſſary for my bodily ſuſtenance, Pſal. 37.19. <hi>In the dayes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine they ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> and becauſe he hath made theſe promiſes, therefore I beleeve them. Finally he hath promiſed to heare any petition that I ſhall make unto him, according to his will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have this confidence in him, and will come boldly to the throne of grace, for <hi>he is faithfull that promiſeth.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing the promiſes, both of temporall and eternall favours, are equally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, and ſeeing God is faithfull in all his promiſes, as well in the one fort, as he is in the other; it muſt needs be that the Saints (unto whom onely the promiſes belong) may and ought, as abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon thoſe, concerning this life, as they may upon thoſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7192:7"/>the life to come. Now that the promiſes are equally abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute (which indeed is the onely thing to proove) it doeth plainely appeare by divers places; firſt the Apoſtle St. Peter in the 2. Epiſtle chap. 1.3. doeth aſſure us, that <hi>the Lord and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hath given unto us all things that pertaine unto life and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Hence it is that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn in his firſt Epiſtle chap. 5. writing to all beleevers in generall (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. theſe things have I written to you that beleeve) he doeth in the 14. verſe include himſelf among the reſt, and plainly declare unto all men, that the manner of their praying was, not onely to ſpeake with the tongue, but alſo with the heart to beleeve that God is faithfull in that very promiſe, contract or covenant, for the obtaining whereof they doe at any time ſue unto him. For (ſaith he) <hi>this is the confidence that we have in him, if we aſke any thing, (.i.) any thing for ſoule or bodie, according to his will,</hi> (.i.) according to his will revealed in his word, <hi>he heareth us. And if we know that he heareth us, whatſoever we aſke, we have the petitions that we deſired of him.</hi> An admirable reſolution of true beleevers; (this is the confidence we have in him) they doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not of his eternall, no nor yet of his temporall promiſes; <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> (as they knew full well) <hi>having the promiſe of both,</hi> 1. Tim. 4.8. If this will not perſwade thee, <hi>(Oh thou of little faith)</hi> abſolutely to depend upon Gods providence and promiſes for temporall neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes; heare what our Saviour himſelf ſayth Iohn 15.7. <hi>If ye abide in me, and my word in you, aſke what ye will, and it ſhall be done unto you;</hi> as if he had ſayd, you abiding in me by faith, and keepe your ſelves within the compaſſe of my word, and then aſke what you will, it ſhall be done unto you. And leaſt any man ſhould thinke, this clauſe <hi>(aſke what you will)</hi> in this our Saviour ſpeech, ought to be reſtraind onely to ſpirituall things, Chriſt himſelfe (who doeth beſt know his owne meaning) doeth expound himſelf Math. 6. For his Diſciples being deſirous to be inſtructed how to pray, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Luke 11.1. Chriſt accordingly was willing and did teach them, as appeareth both by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Luke and alſo by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Mathew in the chapter before quoted, where he doeth expreſly ſpeake of <hi>temporalls.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth he leave it as a thing indifferent, to depend or not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon his promiſes for temporall matters, but he doeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund us in both places abſolutely to pray, and depend upon him for bodyly neceſſaryes, without diſtruſting his will? This doeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7192:8"/>in his owne commandement, which he ſet forth upon the fourth petition in Math. 6.25. to the end of the chapter, where he doeth plainely manifeſt unto us, that the faithfull <hi>ſeekers of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhall not want the comfortable bleſſings of the earth.</hi> His words are very playne, ye find not in them any (If) at all, they are indeed an abſolute promiſe, <hi>Seeke first the Kingdome of God and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Seeke his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the firſt place, bread and cloathing ſhall be given thee in the ſecond place. And to the end no man ſhould doubt at any time of this temporall promiſe, our Saviour doeth uſe in the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtrong reaſons to perſwade us, which are drawne a <hi>minori ad majus,</hi> and we may conceive it thus: <hi>If God</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>thus provide foode for the fowles and birds, and doeth give the graſse ſuch beautiefull cloathing, which to day is, and to morrow is cast into the oven: How much more will he provide for you? But ye ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the Lord doeth provide for the fowles, the birds, and the graſſe: therefore your faith</hi> (which is the evidence of things not ſeene) <hi>ſhould much more teach you, that God</hi> (who is your loving father) <hi>will not faile you.</hi> And more deepely to imprint in the hearts of his hearers the truth of this matter, he doeth ſharply reproove thoſe that ſtagger at the truth of his ſpeech, for he ſaith unto them, <hi>Learne this, oh ye of little faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No marvail then if Paul was ſo bold confidently to avouch this truth to the Romans, ſeeing he tooke his text from our Saviours owne mouth: <hi>He that ſpared not his owne Sonne, but delivered him up for us all; how ſhall he not with him alſo freelie give us all things,</hi> Rom. 8.32. Eſpecially ſeeing (as he againe taught the Corinthians 2. Cor. 1.27.) <hi>in him are the promiſes Yea, and in him Amen.</hi> This was that which Salomon deſired of the Lord 1. Kings 8.38. That if all the people of Iſrael, or any man, did know the <hi>plague in his owne heart,</hi> when any plague was upon them, and ſpread forth his hands unto him, that he would heare in heaven and helpe: which prayer of Salomon the Lord graunted chap. 9.3. Iehoſaphat well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred this promiſe 2. Chron. 20.9. and being in diſtreſſe, he put God in minde of it, and told him that they <hi>could not tell what to doe, but onelie looke upon him, who had promiſed to ſave them.</hi> Now Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat receiving this gracious anſwer from the Lord verſ. 15. to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Lord did remember his promiſe, and would helpe them,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7192:8"/>he preſently verſe 20. turned himſelf to the people, and exhorted them to beleeve this promiſe: for <hi>Iehoſaphat ſtood and ſaid, Heare me, Oh Iudah; and ye inhabitants of Ieruſalem, Beleeve in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall ye be eſtabliſhed: beleeve his Prophets ſo ſhall ye prosper.</hi> Unto which doe our Saviours words agree Mark. 9.23. <hi>All things are poſſible to him that beleeveth.</hi> Where by <hi>all things,</hi> he doeth not onely underſtand things of the ſoule, but alſo whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is comfortable to the body. And this is plainly prooved in the ſame place; for the father by faith received a temporall bleſſing for his child, <hi>for the dumbe and deafe ſpirit came out of him.</hi> verſ. 26. A cloud of witneſſes have their faith extolled, for apprehending tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall favours, for they all <hi>judged him faithfull that promiſed,</hi> Heb. 11.11. And hence it was that David was confident for temporall neceſſaries Pſal. 23.1. <hi>The Lord is my ſhephard, I ſhall not want.</hi> Read that 11. of the Hebr. and there is a whole catalogue commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their faith, eſpecially and in the firſt place for judging God <hi>faithfull</hi> in temporall promiſes. I dare not, then teach any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then that the promiſes, which are made for temporall neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, are <hi>abſolute,</hi> and that we ought abſolutely, without wavering, depend upon them, and judge him faithfull that promiſeth, ſeeing I have my text given me by Moſes from Levit. 26. and Deuter. 28. as alſo by our Saviour himſelf Math. 6. where he doeth allow and maintayne the doctrine of Moſes, unto whoſe ſpirits our ſpirits muſt be ſubject.</p>
            <p>Great reaſon then there is, why the Saints of God both may and ought abſolutely relye and depend upon the promiſes, as for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſo for temporall neceſſaries. Firſt it is commaunded 1. Ioh. 3.23. <hi>This is his commaundement, that we ſhould beleeve on the name of his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſecondly he hath made a way for us, that we may come freely to the throne of grace, where we may ſtand, not trembling as enimies, but boldly as freinds, not doubtfull as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but certaine, as ſonnes, of Gods favour towards us. For by Chriſt we are made the ſonnes of God, and heyres of the promiſes, who hath alſo given unto us ſuch priviledge, <hi>ut Deum blandiſſimo Patris nomine invocare nobis liceat;</hi> that it is lawfull for us to invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate God through him, by that excellent comfortable name of a loving Father. <hi>Num ergo dubitabimus,</hi> (ſaith one) and ſhall wee now doubt, that a loving Father, full of pitty and compaſſion, will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7192:9"/>deny his ſonnes any thing, which he hath commaund them to aſke, and promiſed to give? Oh no, this was to judge him unfaithfull that promiſeth, and to make God a <hi>lyer</hi> (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn ſayth) <hi>he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not God, hath made him a lyer,</hi> 1. Iohn 5.10. Let this our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then (dearely beloved) remaine good by authority from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Prophets, from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, namely, that the promiſes for temporall neceſſaries are abſolute, and may and ought abſolutely be depended upon by his ſervants, without wavering, and then I doubt not, but in the laſt place (this being graunted) thou wilt find and confeſſe this alſo to be true: That the cauſe is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine them, which is our third and laſt head, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging as a branch from the roote of the former heads, and comes next to be prooved.</p>
            <p>The two former heads being graunted to be true, which (if truth take place) it cannot be otherwiſe, this alſo muſt of neceſſity fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. For abſolute faith being required in all prayer, the promiſes concerning life and godlyneſſe, upon which faith is grounded, being of the ſame nature, it muſt needs follow in the 3 place, <hi>that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doeth pray for theſe temporarie things, the fault is in themſelves, if they doe not obtaine them.</hi> God is not, neither can he be ſayd to be wanting. But they are wanting. Now that, we may make this cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, we muſt ſearch the Scriptures, and there enquire of God, how many things he doeth require to be in all ſuch prayers of his ſervants, which he hath promiſed to grace with a gracious anſwer, which is (indeed) a giving to him, or them his poore petitioners, the very thing, or things petitioned.</p>
            <p>The particular things required in prayer (as we find them recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures) are five. Whereof three are ſpecified in one verſe 1. Timoth. 2.8. <hi>I will therefore</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that men pray everie where lifting up holie hands without wrath and doubting,</hi> the fourth is ſpoken of by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames 4.33. <hi>Wee muſt not aſke any thing at the hands of God, for any by-reſpect, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it on our lusts.</hi> The 5 and laſt thing required to be obſerved in prayer, is declared by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn 1. Epiſt. 5.14. wee muſt aſke what we <hi>aſke according to his will.</hi> The want of ſome or one of theſe doubtleſſe, is the cauſe why God doth ſtop his eare at the cry of his ſervants, when they pray unto him for things neceſſary, either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſoule or body. Of theſe five particulars we will ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7192:9"/>as they lye in order, that we may the eaſier diſcerne unto which of theſe (when we aſke and miſſe) the fault is to be imputed (for to the want of ſome, or one of theſe, it muſt needs be) and firſt of the firſt. It is required that we <hi>lift up holie hands.</hi> To lift up ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hands in this place, is all one as if he had ſayd, <hi>lift up holie hearts.</hi> For <hi>manuum elevatio mentem elevandam eſſe docet.</hi> So that the Apoſtles meaning in this place doth agree with that of the Heb. 10.22. where he doth wiſh us to draw neere to God with a <hi>true heart,</hi> (.i.) with a ſincere heart, <hi>ab hypocriſi alieno,</hi> voyd of hypocriſie, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led alſo of the Apoſtle in another place 1. Timoth. 1.5. <hi>Cor purum,</hi> a pure heart, or a heart purely affected, and as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to the Heb. in the place before quoted, <hi>a heart purified from an evill conſcience,</hi> which is all one with that of Paul to Timothy, in the place before recited, where he calls it a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> So then the Apoſtle doth require every one of us, before wee preſume to make prayer unto God, to be truely exerciſed in the works of humiliation and repentance. Every man muſt <hi>know the plague of his owne heart,</hi> 1. Kings 8.38. .i. (as is ſpecified in the ſame chapter verſ. 47.) <hi>Hee muſt bethinke himſelf and repent,</hi> before he can exſpect that the Lord will give an eare to his prayer, nay this muſt be done before he have any warrant to pray at all.</p>
            <p>Now that the want of lifting up holy hands unto God in prayer, (.i.) the want of a pure heart, a good conſcience; or of humiliation and repentance (as we are to underſtand the words) is one cauſe why God doth ſtop his eares at the cry of his ſervants, the Lord himſelf doth plainely teſtify; for this purpoſe read Iſay. 1. where ye ſhall finde that the Lord doth complaine of Iſraels rebellion, and doth even upbraide their whole ſervice. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitudes of your ſacrifices to me, ſaith the Lord? Bring no more vaine obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Your new moones, and your appointed Feaſts, my ſoule hateth: They are a trouble unto me, I am wearie to beare them.</hi> And (ſayth he verſ. 15.) <hi>When ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: Yea when you make manie prayers, I will not heare: Your hands are full of blood.</hi> Agreeing to this, is that of the Prophet Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary in his 7. chapter, where the people enquired of the Lord, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould <hi>weepe in the 5. moneth, and ſeperate themſelves as they had theſe ſo manie yeares?</hi> unto which queſtion the Lord anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by reprooving them in the 5.6.7. verſes, where hee doth tell
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7192:10"/>them, that when they did faſt and weepe thoſe 70. yeares, they did it not unto <hi>him, but for themſelves,</hi> they ſhould have <hi>heard the words which the Lord cryed by the former Prophets,</hi> which indeed they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not. Wherefore the Lord bids the Prophet tell them what they ſhould doe, verſ. 9.10. when they did pray unto him, and faſt, and wept unto him. They had indeed faſted and wept a long time, even 70. yeares, but they prevayled not with God. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet gives the reaſon verſ. 12. <hi>They refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the ſhoulder, and ſtopped their eares that they ſhould not heare, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore juſt it was with God, to deale with them as he did verſ. 13. for he <hi>cryed and they would not heare, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they cryed, he would not heare,</hi> as (in that place) he with his owne mouth doth witneſſe. Iuſtly then may the Lord (when the people tranſgreſſe and rebell againſt him, and will not be humbled) <hi>hide and cover himſelf</hi> (as the Prophet ſayth Lament. 3.44.) <hi>with a cloud, that their prayer ſhall not paſſe thorough, and not ſo much as once</hi> (as he ſpeaketh Levit. 26.81.) <hi>ſmell the ſavour of their ſweete odours.</hi> If thou regard evill in thy heart, the Lord will not heare thee. Thou mayeſt ly crying upon thy face with Ioſuah, but you ſhalt have the ſame anſwer with him, Ioſ. 7.10. wherefore lyeſt thou upon thy face, Iſrael have ſinned. Oh then doe not ſo much as once ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine with thy ſelf, that ever God doth deprive thee of any promiſed favour, or bring upon thee any threatned puniſhment, which thy ſinne doth not cauſe. The Prophet Amos ſaith chap. 3.6. that there is no evill in the citty, (.i.) no evill of puniſhment, but the Lord hath done it; and Ieremy ſayth, that every ſuch evill is an infliction for ſinne; <hi>Man ſuffereth for his ſinne,</hi> Lament. 3.39. Which two places (as it is collected to my hand) doe evince thus much, that whatſoever puniſhments doe or have befallen us, whether plague, peſtilence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or the ſword, they all come from the Lord, and that for ſinne. <hi>Manie times</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>did he deliver them, but they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him with their counſell, and were brought low for their iniquitie,</hi> Pſal. 106.43. And againe, <hi>Fooles, becauſe of their tranſgreſſion, and becauſe of their iniquities, are afflicted,</hi> Pſal. 106.17. And may wee not well ſay, when God doth puniſh us with any plague, as Moſes ſayd to Aaron Numb. 16.46. <hi>There is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun.</hi> Surely God never puniſheth his ſervants, but to humble them, and if they will not be humbled with one puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7192:10"/>he will either continue the ſame, as he did to Iſrael, Iudg. 6. or els bring ſome new one upon them, as he did Amos the fourth. He will puniſh them firſt in their goods, deprive them of outward comforts, and if that will not ſerve to bring them to repentance, he will lay it upon their bodyes, and ſend the peſtilence among them, after the manner of Egypt, and if they will not be reformed for theſe things, he will (as he ſaith Levit. 26.) <hi>puniſh them ſeven times more for their ſinnes,</hi> as it is often repeated in that chapter. Hence it is that the Prophet doth complaine of the forlorne Iewes, for that they would not be humbled by puniſhments, <hi>Thou haſt ſmitten them, but they have not ſorrowed: Thou haſt conſumed them, but they have refuſed to receive correction,</hi> Ierem. 5.3. Yea many blowes are given, but the people <hi>turne not to him that ſmiteth,</hi> Iſay. 9.13. This made the Lord himſelf to cry out Iſay. 1.5. <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſtriken anie more? Ye will revolt more and more.</hi> What doe all theſe point out unto us, but that thoſe puniſhments, which God layeth upon his people, are to humble them for their ſinnes? and that their great impenitency doth even ſtand as a cloud betweene God and them, to keepe their prayers from him? What now muſt be done in this caſe? muſt we continue in ſinne? and lye as it were ſenceleſſe under Gods puniſhing hand? For anſwer, hearke what God himſelf ſayth, Iſay 1.16. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye cleane, put away the evill of your doings, from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe evill, learne to doe well, &amp;c.</hi> Come now let us reaſon together, and by repentance (Amos 4.12.) <hi>prepare to meete thy God, Oh Iſrael.</hi> This is the way, walke in it: Thou ſeeſt impenitence, and hardneſſe of heart, is one thing, which doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both the courſe of Gods bleſſing from thee, as alſo bring all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments unto thee, which are inflicted upon thee. Heare thou the ſumme of this whole matter, thou muſt know the plague in thy owne heart, or els Gods plague cannot be remooved from thee, all thy cryes will not moove him, unleſſe in the firſt place thy hands be holy.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the firſt thing required in prayer; It is a lifting up of holy hands. The ſecond followeth: It muſt be <hi>without wrath,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. (.i.) It muſt be done without wrath, unto which chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is oppoſed. In theſe words, when he ſayth, <hi>pray without wrath,</hi> it is all one as if he had ſayd, Pray in charity. That charity is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when wee pray for temporall or eternall favours, the words of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7192:11"/>the Apoſtle in this place, is ſufficient to proove. But it is ſeconded againe 1. Cor. 16.14. <hi>Let all your things be done in charitie.</hi> If all things then muſt be done in charity, then prayer ought not to be done without it. And the Apoſtle doth give the reaſon 1. Cor. 13.1.2. without this our prayers are nothing, it is but <hi>as a ſounding braſse, and as a tinkling cymball. He that loveth not</hi> (ſayth Iohn 1. Epiſt. 4.8.) <hi>knoweth not God, for God is love.</hi> And how then can it be, that any one can pray to him a right, of whoſe knowledge he is ignorant? <hi>Charitie</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle Coll. 3.14.) <hi>is the bond of perfectneſse.</hi> If the bond be broken, by which the Saints are all lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together, as one man, all things muſt needs be out of order. <hi>Evacuanda ergo est mens,</hi> the ſoule muſt be emptied of this humor when we pray. Lift up holy hands, <hi>ſine ira,</hi> without wrath. Now that the want or fayling in this duety of charity, when we pray unto God, is another cauſe why God doth ſtop his eares at the cry of his ſervants, either when they pray for a promiſed favour, or for the avoyding of any puniſhment, we need not ſtand long in prooving. Take onely that ſaying of the Prophet Zach. 7.10. and compare it with that of the Apoſtle 1. Cor. 13.5. and the point is clearely juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. The Apoſtle doth ſhew us what charity is, a part of whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in that verſe is contained, <hi>It thinketh not evill.</hi> To thinke evill then, is againſt the lawes of charity. Now the Prophet affirmeth, that the thinking or imagining <hi>evill one against another in their hearts,</hi> was one ſpeciall thing, why God did not hearken to their prayers, notwithſtanding they containued, crying <hi>70 Yeares.</hi> No marvail then, if in our times many prayers be made to God invaine, which never receive an anſwer, ſeeing they imagine ſo much evill in their hearts of their brethren. Nay it breaks out now beyond imagination, their imaginations break out into practiſe. Strange it is to conſider, that Chriſtians of all others, ſhould be ſo unnaturall. Yet not ſo ſtrange as true: for (as one ſayth) <hi>the hand ſearcheth the eye, the mouth biteth the hand: Thornes and briers imbrace one another, while</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all nature) <hi>figtrees devoure one another.</hi> Now if men ſhall ſuck, even ſuck the blood one of another, concoct their moyſture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to malice, imagine evill in their hearts one of another, and thus vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the lawes of charity; How can they exſpect to receive any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or remoove any puniſhing hand of God from them, when they pray unto him? was the imagining of evill one againſt another (the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7192:11"/>leaſt breach, as ſome judge of the lawes of charity) one ſpeciall thing, which as a cloud did ſtand betweene God and Iſraels prayers, and ſhall not imaginations and practiſes, and all joyned together, ſtand betweene him and men now? Surely God is the ſame God, and there is ſtill the ſame effect of ſinne. It will ſtill (not being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of) ſtoppe the current of Gods bleſſings from us, and pull downe upon us tokens of his diſpleaſure. Which tokens of his anger (untill it doth bring forth the fruits of humiliation) will ſticke as faſt as Gehaſies leproſie: It will not be remooved. And thus of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing required in prayer.</p>
            <p>The third followeth. It muſt be without doubting. Doubting in this place is oppoſed to faith, for indeed they are contrary, where faith is, doubting is not, and where doubting is <hi>(codem inſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</hi> faith cannot be, for faith admits not of doubting. In theſe words, when he ſayth, <hi>Pray without doubting,</hi> it is all one as if he had ſayd, Pray with faith. Doubt not at all when ye pray. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here uſed by the Apoſtle, doth properly ſignify, <hi>ſine diſceptatione,</hi> and ſo Beza doth tranſlate it. So that the Apoſtles meaning (as it may be gathered from the nature of the word) is this; he would have us, when wee pray, to be ſo farre from doubting, as that wee ſhould not ſo much as queſtion, or diſpute in any doubtfull manner, or ſay as the Serpent did to the woman Gen. 3.1. <hi>Yea hath God ſaid.</hi> But when we urge God for his promiſes by prayer, he would have us to doe it (wee ſee) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſine diſceptatione,</hi> without diſputing, without doubting. Now further to proove that doubting ought to be excluded, and that faith is required in all prayer, we need not any longer to inſiſt upon it in this place, but referre you to our former grounds, where it is fully manifeſted. Now that the want of faith is another cauſe, why God doth ſtop his eares at our prayers, it is eaſily juſtifiable by the Scriptures. And indeed the truth is, wee may ſay of faith in prayer, as our Saviour did of thoſe great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, upon this hangs all the reſt. Where this is truely, there all the other foure things, required in prayer, muſt needs be. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man come to God with humiliation, and with love, unleſſe he aſke for the true ends, and according to Gods revealed will, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to have faith: well he may have a kinde of ſwimming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, to have the thing petitioned, but faith he cannot have. Where faith is, there are accompaning her all theſe attendants, but where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7192:12"/>ſhe is not, there her attendants will not prevaile. Faith is the key of the whole worke. The want of this, ſpoyles all. Now that the lack of faith, a wavering, or doubting, is alſo a ſpeciall cauſe, why the Saints doe often goe away empty from the throne of grace, it is plainly made manifeſt in divers places. It is ſayd of our Saviour Mat. 13.58. (in whom there is neither want of power or will) that <hi>he did not many mightie workes there, becauſe of their unbeliefe.</hi> Calvine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place is of this opinion; for he repeatingly uſing theſe words of Auguſtine, <hi>Faith is very aptlie compared to certaine veſſels with open mouth: but infidelitie is like to a cover, with the which the veſsells are covered, that it cannot receive the liquor poured in by the Spirit of God.</hi> Unto which compariſon of Auguſtine Calvine doth aſſent, as his owne words doe witneſſe, <hi>And truelie</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. For the Lord, ſeeing that his power is not received of us, doth at the length take away the ſame, and yet notwithstanding afterwards we complaine, that we want his helpe, which our incredulitie and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse of heart, hath repelled and driven away.</hi> Unto this alſo doth Gualter ſubſcribe in one of his Homilies (upon theſe words, <hi>And he could doe there no mightie workes,</hi> Mark. 6.) his words are theſe, <hi>Admonemur igitur hoc exemplo, &amp;c.</hi> we are taught by this example, how it comes to paſſe, that we are at this day deprived of many bleſſings: <hi>Nimirum</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>quod pauciſſimos invenire licet vere credentes, &amp;c.</hi> And hence it is that he breaketh out into this dolefull complaint, <hi>Eſt autem haec gravis &amp; horribilis infidelitatis poena, quod Christi virtutem nobis infrugiferam, &amp;c.</hi> Oh what a grievous and horrible puniſhment of infidelity is this! It doth cauſe both the power and vertue of Chriſt to be unfruitfull unto us, and make us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unable and unworthy to pertake of it. What doe thoſe words before recited proove, but (according to the judgement alſo of thoſe Divines) that the want of faith, in apprehending the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, doth deprive us of many bleſſing, as well concerning the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as the ſoule. This word <hi>(If)</hi> in prayer, is but a little word, but yet it ſtands betweene God and us as a cloude; it doth deprive us of many favours. So long as this <hi>If,</hi> ſtood betweene Chriſt and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the 9. of Marke, and the 22. it kept him from the bleſſing, but being afterwards remooved, his requeſt was graunted, his child was diſpoſſeſſed of a dumbe and deafe ſpirit at the ſame inſtant. Moſes was deprived of a temporall bleſſing, Numb. 20.12. and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7192:12"/>cauſe is imputed to <hi>Titubatio fidei,</hi> to the halting of his faith, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry juſtly to; for the Lord himſelf ſaith, (in the place before quoted) <hi>becauſe ye beleeved me not, to ſanctifie me in the eyes of the children of Iſrael, therefore ye ſhall not bring this congregation into the land, which I have given them.</hi> And the Pſalmiſt ſaith 106.32. <hi>That it went ill with Moſes, notwithſtanding the people provoked his ſpirit, ſo that he ſpake unadviſedly with his lippes.</hi> No marvaill then, if the want of faith doth in theſe laſt times deprive the Saints of God of many bleſſings, ſeeing Moſes himſelf for lack of this, came ſhort of the promiſed <hi>Canaan.</hi> If men feare and doubt with Peter Math. 14.30. no marvaill if they <hi>ſinke</hi> with <hi>Peter.</hi> And great reaſon there is, that the ſame ſaying ſhould be applyed to ſuch as doubt of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall promiſes, as Chriſt applyed to Peter (verſ. 31.) <hi>Oh thou of little faith, wherefore doest thou doubt?</hi> Now to prevent all prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate opinions, concerning this which hath bene ſpoken: Note by the way, that when we affirme that the lacke of neceſſaries, is to be imputed to the lacke of faith, in apprehending the promiſes, we doe not call that ſaith of Gods ſervants into queſtion, which they have in Chriſt Ieſus, for apprehending the pardon of their ſinnes, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, whereby they are juſtified before God; for we affirme, that a man may have faith to juſtify himſelf before God, and yet want faith in apprehending a temporall promiſe. So then, we are to diſtinguiſh faith into two ſorts: The one is called juſtifying or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall faith, and ſo called, becauſe the object it eyeth, is of an eternall nature, it apprehendeth eternall promiſes. The other ſort of faith is termed temporary faith, and ſo termed, becauſe the object it eyeth, is ſome temporall thing, this apprehendeth onely temporall promiſes. Both which ſorts of faith is required in Gods ſervants: the power of one, to keepe his ſoule to eternall life. The other, to preſerve and provide neceſſaries for the body, while God ſhall give him life; for <hi>the just ſhall live by faith.</hi> Now theſe two ſorts of faith being divers in reſpect of their ſeverall object, each of them ought to be referred to his proper object. Eternall, or juſtifying faith, to eternall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: and temporary faith, to temporall promiſes. So then, as you ſay (and that truely) whoſoever commeth ſhort of heaven, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanteth faith, in apprehending the eternall promiſes. So we affirme (and that truely) that whoſoever wanteth bread, it is becauſe he lacketh faith, in apprehending the temporall promiſes. And theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7192:13"/>two kinds of faith are both the gift of God, and enimies to doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: So doubtings are fruits of our corrupt nature, and meere op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites to faith in any of the promiſes, which doth deprive us of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſings. And ſo I paſſe from this third thing required in prayer, it muſt be without doubting; unto the 4. ſet downe by Iames, that it muſt be deſired for the true ends, not to <hi>conſume it upon our lusts.</hi> That we ought to ayme at the true ends, which indeed is the glory of God, when we pray for any thing, our Apoſtle doth plainely proove 1. Cor. 10.31. <hi>Whether ye eate or drinke, or whatſoever ye doe, doe all to the glorie of God.</hi> The glory of God ought to be the center of all our actions, as well of prayer, as of any other action. And the truth is, this is the true rule of prayer, to aſke, not ſo much becauſe we would receive, as we doe becauſe God hath commanded us, and we beleeve that God will give us the thing petitioned, not for our prayers ſake, but becauſe he hath promiſed. To aſke in this manner, is to aſke for the true ends, that we may not conſume it upon our luſts. To aſke, becauſe God hath commanded us, doe ſhew our obedience: To beleeve that we ſhall have the thing we aſke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath promiſed, doth manifeſt Gods faithfullneſſe, and both makes for the advancement of his glory.</p>
            <p>Now that the not-walking by this rule, doth deprive us of the thing petitioned, we need uſe no other place then that of Iames be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoted, Iames 4.3. <hi>Ye aſke and receive not, becauſe ye aſke amiſſe, that ye may conſume it upon your lusts. Men</hi> (as one ſaith) <hi>often ſeeke</hi> Bona, <hi>good things;</hi> Non bene, <hi>not in a good manner.</hi> If it were not onely for ſome hope they had to receive ſome benefit by Chriſt, many would (as the Prophet ſpeaketh Iſay 53.3.) <hi>hide their faces from him, they would despiſe him, and eſteeme him not.</hi> The principall drift of their ſeeking to Chriſt, is their owne ends. They ſeeke him for their owne benefit, more to receive, then by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, Gods name might be gloryfied, by which meanes they doe not to their comfort find; hee will not be found of ſuch ſeekers. Theſe ſeekers doe altogether befoole themſelves in their ſearch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they altogether ayme at their owne ends. Now if any of the petitions of the Saints of God be infected with this diſeaſe, if they ſeeke in their requeſts at any time, when they pray, <hi>Aliud pro illo, aliud prae illo,</hi> ſomething inſtead of his glory, ſomething beſids his glory, ſome thing with his glory, ſome thing before his glory, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7192:13"/>doe not ſeeke every thing for his glory. No marvaill if they ſeeke and miſſe, ſeeing they <hi>ſeeke amiſse.</hi> And thus from that 4. I proceed to the laſt thing required in prayer: wee muſt pray, for what wee doe pray, according to his will. The will of God (although in reſpect of himſelf is but ſimply one) in reſpect of us is twofold. The one is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, not revealed to Angels or to men; This is altogether incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable, neither can theſe ſecrets be knowne to any, but the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and for any to ſtrive to dive into them, is too much curioſity. The other is revealed, the knowledge whereof is left obtainable by man; for the great God of heaven and earth, hath bene pleaſed to have bene examined, <hi>ad perpetuam rei memoriam,</hi> and hath left his will (ſo much of his will as is neceſſary for man to know) regiſtred in his Word, which will muſt be the onely directrixe of all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, <hi>If we aſke any thing</hi> (ſayth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn) <hi>according to his will,</hi> according to his will revealed in his Word. That all our petitions, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning ſoule or body, ought to be framed according to Gods will, I thinke its not denied of any. But here lyeth the queſtion; when are our petitions agreable with the will of God? Some affirme that the particle, <hi>If,</hi> doth make the petition accord with the will of God, but without ground from any part of his word. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we affirme, that, <hi>If,</hi> in prayer for temporall things, doth not make the petitions accord with the will of God, but it doth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make it diſagree from the will of God, for our petitions are agreable to the will of God, when they are agreable to his word. Now our petitions for outward things, are agreable to Gods will, not when wee put in this word <hi>If,</hi> as to ſay, If it be thy will to give us this or that; but they are agreable to his will, when the thing wee deſire God to beſtow upon us, is both commanded and promiſed. This is that which doth make our petitions agreable to his will. And therefore when we are to pray, either for any favour, or for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooving of any affliction, we muſt conſider with our ſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be within the compaſſe of this rule, namely, whether God in his word doth command us to aſke ſuch a thing, which we deſire to have, and whether he doth promiſe upon our calling, to beſtow it upon us; and not rudely, and unadviſedly, nay ignorantly upon all occaſions, runne to God onely with an <hi>If.</hi> Hence it is, when the Saints doe come to the throne of grace, and ſolicite God in Ieſus Chriſt, for any favour, that the holy Ghoſt doth put them upon that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7192:14"/>iſſue, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> produce your evidence, where have I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you in the Scriptures to aſke of me ſuch and ſuch a bleſſing? where is your warrant? Where in my Scriptures have I made any ſuch contract, any ſuch covenant, any ſuch promiſe, to give you ſuch or ſuch a thing, which ye deſire of me? Now if the Saints ſo praying, are able to produce their evidence, and ſay unto the Lord, Loe, here is our warrant, thou haſt commanded us in thy word to aſke this thing which wee now deſire, and therefore in obedience to thy command, wee have this boldneſſe to come unto thee; and loe, Oh Lord (pointing as it were with the finger to the place) here is our evidence; in thy Scriptures thou haſt made a contract, a covenant, a promiſe to give us the thing we now deſire. If I ſay the Saints can thus anſwer the Spirit, and produce their evidence, as afore-ſayd, their petition is lawfull, and they may lawfully charge God with his promiſe, his contract, his covenant. But then when the Spirit of God puts them to that iſſue, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> produce your evidence for what ye aſke, and they are not able to produce any, either commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or promiſe, deducted from his Scriptures, he may (as one ſaith) juſtly plead, and anſwer ſuch <hi>Petitioners,</hi> with a <hi>Non est factum,</hi> I made no ſuch promiſe. Wherefore when men pray unto God for ſuch things, as have no ground from his Word (notwithſtanding they thruſt in an <hi>If</hi>) they ſhall be ſent away empty, the Lord will plead to ſuch petitioners, <hi>Non eſt factum,</hi> I made no ſuch promiſe. He delighteth not in ſuch babling. It is a common evill among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men profeſſing Religion, to pray for all things, but ſcarſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve any thing. They will pray for all things that can be imagined with an If, but with an If, or without an If, they can beleeve but little; for <hi>when the ſonne of man cometh</hi> (Luke 18.8.) <hi>ſhall he find faith on the earth?</hi> It is we ſee then, Gods word, (the Scriptures) not any mans word (this If) which maketh our petitions agreeable to the will of God. And did not Chriſt labour ſo to inſtruct his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that they ſhould aſke for nothing, but for ſuch things which are well-pleaſing to God, <hi>Dum brevi &amp; dilucida formula com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexus est, quaecunque nos à Deo petere convenit,</hi> when as he compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth in ſuch a ſhort and admirall forme, what was meete to be deſired?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Huic ſi accommodemus preces noſtras</hi> (ſaith Gualter) <hi>nunquam creabimus.</hi> Out of which forme of Chriſt (ſaith one) <hi>excellent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7192:14"/>might be gathered, concerning the thing in hand. Firſt Christ teacheth us to pray for bread, (.i.) for things neceſſary for our preſent being. He commands not to pray for great things, for aboundance, for ſuperfluity. If we aſke them, no marvaill if we uſe an If. Secondly we are taught to pray for our dayly bread, (.i.) for things neceſsary for the preſent day we live in (and not to be troubled about to morrow, Math. 6.34.) No marvaill then, if we thruſt in an If, praying for bread againſt the next day, as not content with our Omer of Manna for the preſent day.</hi> By this ye may plainely ſee, (contrary to a falſe imagined imputation) that wee doe not limite and confine Gods will to mens wills, and to what they will deſire: but wee confine and limite (as Chriſt hath taught us) mans will to Gods will, and that his deſire ought not to ſwell above its limits. Wee muſt aſke onely what he hath commanded, and exſpect to receive onely that which he hath promiſed. This is to aſke according to his will, and to aſke according to his will, ye ſee, is to ground our prayers upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and promiſes, revealed unto us in his word, his written verity; preſuming upon nothing that is not therein regiſtred, and doubting of nothing that is therein warranted. <hi>He that walketh</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in an other caſe Gal. 6.16.) <hi>according to this rule, peace be upon him, and mercy, and upon the Iſraell of God.</hi> Wee have now gone over every one of theſe 5 particulars, which God requireth in prayer, and we ſee the fayling in ſome or one of them, will cauſe our prayers to recoyle and turne againe into our owne boſomes.</p>
            <p>But when they all meete together, they doe ſend up our prayers unto heaven as a ſweet ſmelling ſavour, God will not, nay hee can not deny us the thing we deſire of him, whether pertaining to this life or the life to come, becauſe <hi>he is faithfull that promiſeth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the thing we pray for</hi> (as ſaith a zealous and learned Doctor) <hi>be within the compas of theſe things which God hath promiſed to give, he can no more deny our requeſt, then he can deny himſelf, if</hi> (obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the things before ſpecified) <hi>we continue in prayer.</hi> Call now to mind our former grounds, and this alſo will unreſiſtably follow. The fault is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine at the hands of God the very thing petioned. They faile in one of theſe particulars; either they know not the plague in their owne hearts, or els they faile in the duety of charity (ſo that as Chriſt ſpeaketh Mark. 11.25.) <hi>they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7192:15"/>forgive not when they pray,</hi> either they want faith, which is as a hand to receive the bleſſing, or els the thing they require is not within the compaſſe of Gods commandement and promiſe, or els they aſke it for by-ends, and to conſume it upon their luſt: And then no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaill (ſaith Gualter) <hi>ſi nec exaudimur à Deo, &amp; inſuper gravioribus malis involvimur.</hi> If then thou doeſt aſke a gift, and miſſe, ſo that thou haſt juſt cauſe to be aſhamed of thy hope in that particular, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute not the fault unto God, and ſay hee was unwilling to give: but lay the fault where it is, accuſe thy ſelf and ſay; I was unfitted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: either in wanting or failing in ſome or one of thoſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecified, required in prayer. The Devill it may be contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this courſe, will tell thee in thine care, that thou art cleare in the matter, hee will labour (according to his old uſe) to lull thee a ſleepe in ſecurity, and perſwade thee that thou haſt performed thy duety, he will tell thee, that thou haſt prayed as well as any, and that thou haſt repentance and humiliation enough, and that thy love doth abound, nay he will perſwade thee, that thou haſt faith alſo in the promiſe, and that for thy part thou doeſt not faile in any particular, required in prayer, notwithſtanding thou doeſt miſſe of the thing thou prayeſt for. This he will ſeeme alſo to make good by this gloſſe: that which thou deſireſt of God (although it be commanded to be aſked, and promiſed to be given) is not good for thee. But learne this (oh thou man of God) that this is but the hiſſing of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, beleeve him not. For know this for certaine, that as humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and love, and faith, &amp;c. is the gift of God: So the Lord never giveth them to any, but withall he giveth the thing faithed. For if they affirme, they have humiliation, and love, and faith, and yet have not the thing faithed, (.i.) they miſſe of the very thing mentioned, which in their petition muſt be the thing faithed, they make God a deceiver, becauſe he never gives the one without the other; if he gives faith and repentance, and the reſt required in prayer, hee will without all doubt give the thing deſired too. And therefore when we begge, and goe without the thing deſired, it is (as we ſayd before, it cannot juſtly be denyed) becauſe we faile in ſome or one of thoſe things required in prayer. But ſtay (ſay ſome) you runne on a pace, what? are none deprived of temporall bleſſings, but upon the want of faith and repentance, or upon their failing in ſome or one of thoſe forenamed particulars? what then ſhall we thinke of many of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7192:15"/>Gods deare children, who for the Goſpell and truths ſake, in caſe of perſecution, are not onely deprived of things neceſſary for this life, but alſo of life it ſelf; what? ſhall we impute theſe their ſufferings to their want of faith and repentance, or to their failing in any other particular; what? may they alſo pray abſolutely to be delivred? and if they are not delivered, is the fault theirs too? To remoove this doubt (which ſome thinke doth contradict the point in hand) wee are to conſider, that perſecution for the teſtimony of faith, and a good conſcience, is the legacy and portion of the faithfull, as appeareth Math. 10. when our Saviour doth tell his Diſciples, that they were ſent forth as ſheep among wolves, and that they ſhould be hated of all men for his names ſake, and that many would thinke, that <hi>they did God good ſervice to kill them,</hi> Ioh. 16.2. and therefore he tells them verſ. 33. that in the world they ſhould have tribulation. Neither is this the portion onely of the Apoſtles, but alſo of every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth by their preaching, <hi>for all</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle 2. Tim. 3.13.) <hi>that will live godly in Chriſt Ieſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> Now this portion of the Saints is not to be accounted (neither is it) a plague, or a puniſhment upon them, but a bleſſing, as appeareth by our Saviours words Math. 5.10.11. <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for righteouſneſſe ſake, &amp;c.</hi> which words St. Peter repeatingly uſeth 1. Epiſt. 3. and 4. chap. and the 14. verſe. Hence it was (as I conceive, ſeeing to be perſecuted for the truth is ſuch a bleſſed thing) that thoſe tortured Saints (Heb. 11.35.) <hi>accepted not deliverance, that they might obtaine a better reſurrection:</hi> And this made S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul Act. 21.13. willing and ready, <hi>not to be bound onely, but alſo to dye at Ieruſalem for the name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> The promiſes being rightly conſidered, it will follow that we have no warrant to pray at all againſt perſecution, that we ſhall not ſuffer, ſeeing it is our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea and a bleſſed portion too, neither would this petition (put caſe a man did pray) be agreable to Gods will (which was the laſt thing required in prayer,) becauſe hee doth not (for ought I find) command us to pray againſt perſecution, and promiſe us that wee ſhall not ſuffer. All the prayers that they are to make in this caſe, muſt be to deſire the Lord, that he would give them ſtrength and patience manfully to perſevere in the truth, and that hee would make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his glory. In a word then, when the Saints of God in caſe of perſecution for the Goſpells ſake, are taken, and by wicked
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7192:16"/>hands deprived of temporall neceſſaries, as of goods, livings, liberty, and life, and all, we impute not theſe their ſufferings to their want of faith and repentance, (it is their portion, and they ſuffer it joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, Heb. 10.34.) Neither to their failing in any other particular, (God never promiſed that they ſhould not ſuffer) but we ſay as Chriſt ſpeaketh Math. 10.18. <hi>They are brought before Kings and Governours for Gods ſake, for a testimony against them, and the Gentils.</hi> And indeed the ſufferings and perſecutions of the Saints, doe exceedingly redound to Gods glory, 1. Pet. 4.14. So in this caſe, notwithſtanding the Saints doe ſuffer, the promiſe of God, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning outward things, is not nullified, but is ſtill in force; and faſt to the beleever. Neither doth this hinder us from praying abſolutely for temporall neceſſaries in time of freedome, neither can it proove that the faulte is not ours, if in any other caſe wee are deprived of them. For to be deprived of them for the Goſpels ſake, is a bleſſing, and the portion of Gods people, but in any other caſe it is a plague, and a puniſhment for ſinne. The firſt maketh for the advancement of Gods glory, the latter is to worke in thoſe, upon whom it is layd, humiliation and repentance. So that now (the anſwer of this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion being rightly underſtood) we are come againe clearely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rubbe to our former ground. It is this, when we begge and goe without a gift, the thing deſired; it is becauſe we want faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or faile in ſome, or one of theſe particulars, required in prayer, <hi>for as much</hi> (ſayth Cyprian upon the Lords prayer) <hi>as all things are Gods, he that hath God, can want nothing, if he himſelf be not wanting unto God.</hi> What now (dearely beloved) doth all this doctrine tend unto, but to the humbling of us in our wants, as alſo to the juſtifying of God in all his proceedings? Firſt it doth ſerve to the humbling of us in our wants in that, by reaſon of our weakneſſe and corruptions, we have made our ſelves unworthy of many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings. Oh then whatſoever thou art, whenſoever thou prayeſt unto God, and hee will not be found of thee, retire quickly to thine owne heart, be jelous of him, (hee is deceitfull) and ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, Oh wretch! thou haſt cauſed my loving Father to frowne upon me, and cover himſelf in a cloud, ſo that my prayers cannot paſſe thorough, either thou regardeſt ſinne, and hideſt corruption within thee, thou art ſtubborne, and wilt not be mollified, or els thou art hardned too much againſt the face of thy brethren, either thou
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7192:16"/>doubteſt and wavereſt at the promiſe of my loving Father, and doeſt even call his faithfullneſſe into queſtion, who hath alwayes bene faithfull unto me, or els thou doeſt ayme too much at thy owne end, aſking what thou deſireſt (according to thy old cuſtome) to conſume it upon thy filthy luſts. Say (I ſay) unto thy heart, <hi>Oh, hinc illae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae,</hi> (be not beate off it) here is the fountaine of my griefe, why my Father is angry with me. Let him not ſhift thee off, with this or the like poore excuſe. The Lord doth not ſee it good for thee; but rather tell him plainely thou knoweſt, the Lord doth ſee it good for thee, becauſe hee hath both commanded thee to aſke it of him, and hath alſo promiſed to give it, but thou, Oh falſe heart, with ſome or one of thoſe before ſpecified, haſt made me unworthy of the thing which I have aſked, unſufficient to apprehend the promiſe, and to receive it. To bring the heart to this examination, is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent meanes to worke in him humiliation, and certainely it will keepe him in the better awe. This being thus performed in the firſt place, it will alſo in the ſecond place juſtify God in all his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, for when we aſke a lawfull petition of God, and goe without it; If then wee acknowledge that the fault is our owne, if we doe not receive it, wee doe thereby ſubmit our ſelves to Gods juſtice, and acknowledge that whatſoever the Lord hath done unto us, in depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of us of ſuch or ſuch a bleſſing, or continuing upon us ſuch or ſuch a puniſhment, it is all but juſt: there can be no aſpertion of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, no imputation of iniquity layd upon his Majeſtie. Yea by this we acknowledge (nay our ſinnes, our weakeneſſes, our infidelity, our corruptions have taught us to yeeld) that all is juſt, and that there is not the leaſt mixture of wrong in his proceedings. In a word, by this we acknowledge (as David ſaith Pſal. 51.4.) <hi>that he is just in ſpeaking, and cleare in judging.</hi> Such then as maintayne the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrine, doe teach men to arrogate too much to themſelves, and to give unto God too little. Come out then, oh thou <hi>Conditionall,</hi> from among the petitions of the Lords prayer, and ſit downe yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thou waſt never placed there by Chriſts appointment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may boldly ſay of thee, as our Saviour of the plant not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Father Math. 15.13. thou ſhalt be rooted up. Thou haſt robbed God of his glory, thou haſt deprived us of many bleſſings, &amp; a long time lulled us aſleepe in too much ſecurity, as alſo blinded us with too much ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Stand faſt then (oh ye that have put your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7192:17"/>hands to the Lords plough) in that liberty, wherewith Chriſt hath made you free; <hi>hold faſt the profeſſion of your faith without wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring:</hi> Let no man take your crowne; and to uſe the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 1. Epiſt. 5.10. <hi>The God of all grace, who hath called us into his eternall glory by Christ Ieſus, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you, to him be glory, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for ever and ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>EPILOGVS.</head>
            <p>THe manner of our proceeding (ye may dearly beloved ſee, who are contrary minded) in prooving what we affirme, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning prayer, is by a true rule; for what we perſwade any to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, for that wee bring a commandement, and for what wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any to beleeve, wee ſhew a promiſe. This is not the rule of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> but of <hi>Verity.</hi> And therefore if any one ſhall but endeavour to contradict this which hath bene ſayd for abſolute prayer, for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls, I would entreat him to walke according to this rule. Truſt not in a ſtaffe, which is but as an Aegyptian reede, thinke not with arguments to contradict commandements, neither bring reaſons againſt expreſſe promiſes. <hi>For when men</hi> (as one neatly preſſeth) <hi>preſent reaſons of probability, of veriſimilitude, of pious credulity, not deduct out of the Scriptures</hi> (or by them oppoſe commandements) <hi>they fall into that regular irregularity, and into that conſtant levity, which Augustine justly makes the character and ſpecification of an Heretike, to ſeeme to proceed upon reaſons, and not deduce thoſe reaſons from the Scriptures.</hi> Howſoever if reaſons doe ſeeme to have ſome footing from the Scriptures, if they contradict a commandement, or nullify a promiſe, know this, that they ſeeme onely to have that, which they never had. For we beleeve, and beleeve truely, that 1000 arguments and reaſons are not able to contradict the leaſt of Gods commandements, or nullify one of his promiſes. If then ye will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye upon arguments and upon reaſons, to proove your aſſertion, wee cannot joyne with you, but we will joyne with you in that iſſue, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus;</hi> where is your evidence, where is your commandement from Gods Word, to proove that it is our duety to pray as you ſay? And where is the Scripture to proove, that the promiſes for temporall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7192:17"/>neceſſaries are conditionall? If ye will not, either in your diſputation or writing, obſerve this rule, lay your hands upon your mouthes. For (if ye obſerve not this rule in what ye ſpeake or write) wee beleeve and beleeve truely, that wee are not bound to beleeve you. Take heed (ſpecially you that are ſent to teach) how ye teach the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for if ye produce not a commandement to proove what (either in this matter or any other) you teach men to obſerve, you declare unto all men that you come in a meſſage, but not of Chriſts ſending: For all thoſe that come with commiſſion from Chriſt Ieſus, teach men (Math. 28.20.) <hi>to obſerve that</hi> (and that onely) <hi>which he hath commanded them.</hi> Wherefore before we conclude this our diſcours (good Chriſtian brother, unto whoſe view theſe our lines ſhall come) I would in the name of Chriſt Ieſus intreate of thee theſe things: Firſt that thou wouldeſt peruſe all the promiſes with a ſingle eye, without reſpect of perſons. Let not the truth of God fare the worſe, or be diſeſteemed, becauſe it doth paſſe through the mouth of his weakeſt and meaneſt ſervants. Inquire not what he is that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, but what is ſpoken. Eſteeme the truth as it is, from whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it cometh; buy it, but ſell it not, for great is the truth and prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. Say not with thy ſelf as Chriſts country-men ſayd Mat. 13.55. <hi>Is not this the Carpenters ſonne? and are not his brethren and ſisters with us?</hi> But rathet ſay (if thou art inſtructed but by a woman) as that Propheticall Prince &amp; Princely Prophet David ſayd to Abigall 1. Sam. 25.32. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, and bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou which hast taught me to know the counſell of the Lord.</hi> Be not in any wiſe offended at us, neither be carried away with ſuppoſals. Imagine not evill in thy heart, for in ſo doing thou wilt bring more evill upon thine owne head, then thou art aware of. Concerning our ſelves, we confeſſe 1. Cor. 3.5. that <hi>wee are but the Miniſters by whom ye beleeve,</hi> and that which we ſpeake is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth and novell opinion (as ſome judge it) for we <hi>have delivered no more, but what we have received.</hi> Moſes taught it to the Iſraelits, Chriſt to his Apoſtles, his Apoſtles to their hearers, and other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to their Congregations, and wee doe but rayſe that from the dead, which a long time hath layen buried in the pit of oblivion. Receive it then as an ancient truth, not as a novell opinion. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing I would deſire of thee, is, that thou wouldeſt not exerciſe thy wits in carping and quarrelling againſt phraſes or paſſages, or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7192:18"/>againſt any of our quoted Scripturs, againſt which thou thinkeſt thou mayſt except as not ſo pertinent to the purpoſe; let not that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the authority of all the reſt, but rather I would entreat thee (after due examination) thou finding ſome (nay if but one) Scripture which is to that purpoſe, that that may be ſufficient to perſwade thee of the truth of the point, we have now affirmed. For know that the Scriptures are not delivered by tale, but by weight, one place is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to proove a doctrine. And laſtly I beſeech thee, conſider well with thy ſelf, that the point we affirme, is for the faith, and the uſe of it is (as ye have heard) to humble man in his wants, and to juſtify God in all his proceedings. Beware therefore, doe not raſhly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt it. Remember that olde ſaying, <hi>Deliberandum est diu, quod ſtatuendum est ſemel.</hi> Turne over and read with good conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the leaves of the ſacred Bible, before thou publikely oppoſe it. It may be ſome thing may lye hid (yea concerning the thing in queſtion) under thoſe ſacred leaves, which thou didſt never yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Firſt learne what thou holdeſt, then teach it. Follow (as in this matter, ſo in others) S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohns counſell in his 1. Epiſt. 4.1. <hi>Try the ſpirits whether they are of God,</hi> and being tryed, then doe as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul exhorteth 1. Theſſ. 5.21. <hi>hold faſt that which is good, and the Lord give thee underſtanding in all things.</hi> And by his ſpirit direct us all in all truth, enabling us to walke in the truth, preferring Gods glory before all things, that ſo we laying up for our ſelves a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may enjoy the crowne. I will adde no more, but conclude with that of the Apoſtle 1. Cor. 10.15. <hi>I ſpeake as to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:7192:18"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice his 5 Arguments, framed againſt praying abſolutely for temporall things: the Preface of which Arguments (as tis written with his owne hand) runneth verbatim thus; delivered at Gayden the 29 Iunij, againſt praying abſolutely for temporall things, without any condition expreſſed or implyed, and that they want faith that doe not obtaine them, being granted to be neceſſary for the preſent uſe.</head>
            <p>BEfore we come to ſpeake of theſe Arguments, it ſhall not be unmeete to ſpeake ſome-thing of the Title or Preface. Concerning the Preface, we are to conſider in it theſe circumſtances: Firſt theſe Arguments (you ſay) <hi>were delivered.</hi> Now they being delivered, and that publikely too, I make no queſtion but it was done with deliberation and conſideration, for otherwiſe you will come within the compaſſe of the Prophets woe, <hi>Woe be to him, that performeth the worke of the Lord negligently.</hi> Now if you ſpake what you did ſpeake upon deliberation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, if your Arguments proove unſound, unſufficient, and are found to be as ſo many arrowes ſhott againſt the truth, your fault will appeare to be the greater, and certainely you muſt beare your owne blame, and be content to acknowledge your fault, wherein you have offended.</p>
            <p>Secondly you ſay againe, it was delivered againſt <hi>praying abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely for temporall things, without any condition, &amp;c.</hi> By which words you condemne as a ſinne, abſolute prayer for temporall neceſſaries. Now if it be a ſinne (as you affirme, for if it be no ſinne, why doe you reproove it?) to pray to God abſolutely for temporall neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then it muſt needs be the breach of a law, for (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn) <hi>ſinne is the tranſgreſſion of the Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Epist.</hi> 3.4</note> Now if you cannot find a Law
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7192:19"/>(for my part I find not any) againſt this kinde of praying, you went, but God never ſent you to reproove it; for he ſends his meſſengers to reproove no more, but what his word doth condemne as a ſinne. And therefore herein (unleſſe you proove the thing before ſpecified) you muſt confeſſe your fayling.</p>
            <p>Thirdly you thruſt in your Preface this word <hi>(implyed)</hi> which word had you not expreſſed, all your Arguments (as you your ſelf ſhall confeſſe) would not have had ſo much as any colourable ſhew againſt that thing, againſt which you framed them. But of this word more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly you profeſſe alſo that you framed your Arguments againſt this poſition: <hi>That they want faith</hi> (theſe things being prayed for) <hi>that doe not obtaine them.</hi> Concerning which wee thus anſwer, that (upon prayer made for temporall neceſſaries) the want of them is not to be imputed to the want of faith, if we underſtand faith according to the generall definition, as it is defined Heb. 11.1. which is as well the <hi>evidence of things eternall as temporall,</hi> that is, as it apprehendeth both eternall and temporall promiſes, promiſes both concerning <hi>life and godlyneſſe.</hi> I ſay not (I ſay) that thoſe who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their prayer doe not obtaine temporall favours, doe altogether want faith, or have no faith; for I affirme that a man may have faith in apprehending the eternall promiſes, for the pardon of ſinne, and life eternall, and yet want faith in a temporall promiſe, for a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſing, unto the want of which faith in a temporall promiſe, or to the fayling of ſome, or one of faithes companions, I impute the want of theſe outward neceſſaries, as it doth more fully appeare by that which we have ſayd in defence of our tenent, concerning abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute prayer, unto which for your better ſatisfaction, I referre you; and ſo I paſſe from the Title or Preface to the Arguments, as I find them in order written with your owne hand.</p>
            <p>Before we come to ſpeake what we thinke of them, or to ſhew wherein they are fayling; know this (or rather call it to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance) by the way, that for any one to frame Arguments, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to contradict commandements, or nullify promiſes, is no better then publikely and openly to reſiſt the truth. And Auguſtine (as one ſayth) maketh this (and that juſtly) to be the character and ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Heretick, to ſeeme <hi>to proceed upon reaſons or arguments, which have no ſound footing from the Scriptures,</hi> and ſuch arguments
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7192:19"/>have no ſound footing from the Scriptures, when they contradict a commandement, or nullify a promiſe. It had bene well, if theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Arguments had bene free from oppugning thoſe particulars. The Arguments as they lye in order, are theſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice <hi>his first Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THoſe promiſes that have implyed conditions in them, cannot abſolutely be relyed upon, or exſpected, for our faith is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the promiſes.</p>
               <p>But the promiſes of outward things (although but neceſſary) are ſo:</p>
               <p>Therefore they are not abſolutely to be relyed upon or exſpected.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This appeares in 2. caſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Of chaſtiſement and correction, when the Lord will viſite any of his people for their ſinnes, for then doth hee ſtrippe them of their outward comforts in part, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wholely unto death: the former appeares in all the corrections of the faithfull, the latter in the example of the Iewes Lam. 4.4.5. where the parents &amp; children dyed for want of bread, and through extreame famine. Yet they are not charged to want faith for this, neither is faith ſo much required in thoſe caſes, as humiliation and repentance; and who will beare any correction at all at the hand of God, if by his faith hee may preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moove it from him? and how can that be a ſigne of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, that is a ſpeciall teſtimony of Gods love, Rev. 3.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of probation and tryall, when God will proove and try the patience and obedience of his ſervants; for in that caſe they that have bene indued with moſt faith &amp; grace, have bene brought to the greateſt exigents and wants, as in Heb. 11.37. they were deſtitute, afflicted and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 11.27. Paul was pinched with hunger &amp; thirſt, with colde and nakedneſſe, and Luk. 16. Lazarus was in extreame poverty and dyed, yet theſe were full of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7192:20"/>faith, and of the ſpirit of God. Now who would endure theſe tryalls and diſtreſſes, if by faith and prayer hee may remoove them? or with what warrant can he abſolutely pray againſt them, ſeeing no promiſe that ſhall be ſpared, yea how can patience have her perfect worke without them, or faith her crowne and reward, promiſed on that condition: Therefore the promiſes of outward things, have conditions implyed to the people of God, and are not abſolute intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the first Argument.</head>
               <p>THis Argument is to be anſwered <hi>negando,</hi> by denying your Minor propoſition, for ſure I am it is altogether untrue, and contrary to ſound doctrine. To make this appeare, wee are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that Gods will (ſo much of his will as is neceſſary for us to know) is revealed in his Word,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39.</note> his Scriptures, unto which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour referreth the Iewes for to enquire of him, <hi>Search the SCrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they are they that testify of me.</hi> Now the Scriptures, Gods written verities, are abſolutely ſufficient to inſtruct us in all ſaving knowledge, as Paul affirmeth 2. Timoth. 3.15. <hi>Thou hast knowen from a child the holy Scriptures</hi> (ſpeaking of Timothy) <hi>which are able to make thee wiſe to ſalvation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.21.</note> or (as Iames ſayth) <hi>to ſave thy ſoule through faith, which is in Ieſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whereas you affirme that the <hi>promiſes for temporalls are conditionall,</hi> notwithſtanding in the whole Scriptures there is no condition expreſſed, what is it els but to affirme that God hath not revealed ſo much of his will in the Scriptures, as is needfull for us to know; and that the Scriptures are not ſufficient to make the man of God perfect? Your owne words in this matter ſhall be your judge, you ſay that this poſition of yours, namely, <hi>That the promiſes for temporall things are conditionall,</hi> is one of Gods truthes (for you preſſe it upon men to beleeve it as a Truth from God) and yet you ſay, that God hath not expreſſed this Truth is his word, for you ſay it is <hi>implyed.</hi> Now it being implyed and not expreſſed, it is no Scripture, for if it be not expreſſed, it cannot be written, if it be not written, it is none of Gods will, becauſe Gods will (ſo much of his will, as wee muſt know, or beleeve) is all written. To which purpoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7192:20"/>ſaith Chriſt in the place before quoted, <hi>Search</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then to affirme the promiſes of God for temporall things, are conditionall (according to your owne words) is a doctrine of mans owne invention, and not of God. And certainely to make the beſt of it, it is but as one of the Popes unwritten verities. Unwritten you confeſſe it is, for if any man ſhould but aſke you where in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doth God ſay the promiſes are conditionall, you have nothing to anſwer (for ought I know) but this, <hi>The condition is implyed.</hi> To thoſe that come in a pretended meſſage from Chriſt, to beate downe the power of Sathan, and have no better commiſſion from Chriſt, then this, the Devill may boldly ſay as he did Acts 19.15. <hi>Qui vos? Ieſus I know, and Paul I know, but who are yee?</hi> I would I had no worſe enimy then you.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I beſeech you, beware how you maintaine any thing for Gods truth, which is not written (its a chief pillar of the Romiſh Church) leaſt it be ſayd to you, as Paul ſpeaketh,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou that abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Idolls, doeſt thou commit ſacriledge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for thoſe 2 caſes which you alleadge for the prooving of your Minor propoſition (as it will appeare) is not any thing at all to the purpoſe. For your Minor propoſition being denyed, you labour to proove it by theſe caſes thus: Firſt (you ſay) <hi>the Lord for the ſinnes of his people doth ſtrippe them of outward comforts, ſometimes in part, ſometimes wholely unto death;</hi> ergo the promiſes of outward things have conditions implyed in them, and are not abſolutely intended.</p>
               <p>Alas what is this to the purpoſe? or what colour is there in it to proove, that the promiſes are conditionall? for you know and muſt needs confeſſe, that the Lord Levit. 26. and Deuter. 28. made abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to his people Iſrael, pretious promiſes. In which promiſes there is no condition implyed. It is true indeed thoſe promiſes were made upon condition of their obedience, as appeareth in both chapters, <hi>If thou obey the Lord thy God, all theſe bleſſings ſhall come unto thee:</hi> Which condition may be turned participially thus; Thou obeying the commandements of the Lord thy God, &amp;c. The condition in theſe his promiſes lyeth on their part, <hi>If thou obey,</hi> that is, thou obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his commandements; Gods part is abſolute, <hi>all theſe bleſſings ſhall come upon thee:</hi> Doe what I require of thee, and all theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings (without all doubt) ſhall come upon thee, <hi>But if thou wilt not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7192:21"/>obey my commaundements,</hi> (.i.) thou diſobeying my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all theſe curſes ſhall come upon thee. As thy obedience ſhall be rewarded with ſuch and ſuch bleſſings, ſo thy diſobedience ſhall be puniſhed with ſuch and ſuch curſes. The children of Iſrael found the word of God true in theſe particulars, for ſo long as they kept the commaundements of their God, and walked humbly with him, which was the thing he required of them, he was as a <hi>wall of braſſe unto them,</hi> and they wanted nothing of that which he promiſed them, as the whole current of the old Teſtament doth plentifully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But when <hi>they brake his covenant,</hi> and did not obſerve that condition (obedience being all the conditions too) which was made betweene God and them, he brought upon them thoſe plagues which he had threatned. For Iſrael (notwithſtanding they were a choſen people) were very rebellious and unthankfull, as the Lord complayneth of them Iſay. 1. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner, but my people doth not conſider. Ah ſinfull nation, a people laden with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, a ſeede of evill-doers: They have forſaken the Lord, they have provoked the holy one of Iſrael to anger.</hi> Read that 105. Pſalme, there is a whole catalogue of their rebellious proceedings, and how the Lord dealt with them. And to the end the Lord would have no imputation of ſeverity layd upon his Majeſty, for dealing with them as he did, and that no man ſhould once imagine, that hee did faile in his part in the leaſt particular, but was faithfull in all his promiſes, he made it appeare to all the world, that his proceedings with them were juſt; for ſaith he Deut. 39.22. to the end of the chapter, <hi>Their children and the nations ſhall ſay, when they ſee the plagues of that Land, wherefore hath the Lord done this unto this Land? what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the heat of this great anger?</hi> Then men ſhall ſay (verſ. 25.) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have forſaken the covenant of the Lord God of their fathers, which he made with them, when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt.</hi> Here is the Lords proceedings cleared by the confeſſion of all the nations, and the fault layd upon the people, as Ezechiell alſo witneſſeth Ezech. 39.23. as alſo the Prophet Iſay prooveth, Iſay 59.2. to the end of that chapter, <hi>Your iniquities have turned away theſe things, and your ſinnes have withholden good things from you.</hi> Now concerning that place Lament. 46. which you produce, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to proove your poſition, I beſeech you call to mind (I know you know it) that the Lord had a long time before told them, that if
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7192:21"/>they would not heare and obey, he would bring upon them that plague of famine, which the Prophet did there bewaile. This appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Levit. 26. and Deut. 28. where the Lord tells them, if they did not walke with him in obedience, that they ſhould be compelled to eat the fleſh of their ſonnes and daughters, for want of other meat.</p>
               <p>Now Iſrael rebelling againſt the Lord in breaking his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, (for ſhe plucketh away the ſhoulder, ſaith Zachary chap. 7.11.) and forgetting the Lords former kindneſſes, that (as Hoſea ſaith chap. 2.8.) <hi>he had given unto them corne and wine, and wool, &amp; flaxe,</hi> he brought upon them this grievous plague, as it is verſ. 10. <hi>the pittyfull women (according as he had threatned) did eat their owne children for want of other meats.</hi> Neither doth the church goe about to excuſe her ſelf, or lay the leaſt aſperſion upon God for this: for ſhe doth ingeniouſly confeſſe, that it was juſtly come upon her, as appeareth verſ. 12.13. for (ſaith ſhe) <hi>the Kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world would not have beleeved, that the enimy ſhould have entred into the gates of Ieruſalem. Ah</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>but our ſinnes</hi> (contrary to all the worlds judgement) <hi>the ſinnes of our Preiſts and Prophets have cauſed it.</hi> Which words ſhe repeatingly uſeth from the Prophet Ieremy chap. 5.31. as if ſhe had ſayd, <hi>Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſie falſely, and our Preiſts beare rule by their meanes, and we love to have it ſo.</hi> Wherefore (ſaith ſhe againe Lament. 1.18.) <hi>The Lord is righteous, for I have rebelled againſt his commandements.</hi> What now was the cauſe of this plague? your owne words ſhall be the anſwer, <hi>The Lord did viſite them thus for their ſinnes.</hi> What then? would the Lord have layd upon them that plague had they not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled? Surely no. For had they not broken Gods covenant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, they had remayned in their owne borders, and had plenty. And therefore from the promiſes, and from your owne words, wee conclude, that the cauſe why the Iewes were puniſhed with famine, was becauſe they wanted both humiliation for their ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Zach. 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>they hearkened not to the words which the Lord cryed by the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> The plague was ſtill in their <hi>owne hearts,</hi> as alſo becauſe they wanted faith; they could not beleeve that promiſe,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 9.</note> which God made with them, contrary to your words, <hi>yet they are not charged to want faith.</hi> They wanted humiliation for their ſinnes
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See Deut.</hi> 32.20.</note>, which was the cauſe of their puniſhment, and then how is it poſſible to have faith to apprehend that particular deliverance? For had they had faith in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7192:22"/>that particular, they muſt needs have had repentance too: they both goe together.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>Who will beare any correction, if by his faith he may preſently remoove it from him?</hi> Surely for my part I know not any, but would be glad ſo to walke with God in uprightneſſe, as that they might not procure his diſpleaſure, ſo farre as to cauſe him to puniſh them. And I know not any, but are grieved in heart ſo farre to diſpleaſe him, as that he muſt needs puniſh them. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereas you ſay, <hi>how can that be a ſigne of unbeleefe, that is a ſpeciall testimony of Gods love?</hi> I anſwer, it is true, when a Saint of God doth revolte and runne backward, and it may be ly ſleeping in ſome ſinne a pretty while, the Lord, and that out of his love, doth ſtretch forth his hand by laying ſome judgement upon him, which is as a warning-peale to ſtay him, and to <hi>bring back his ſoule from the pit.</hi> To which purpoſe is that place Revel. 3.19. <hi>As many as I love I rebuke and chasten:</hi> What follows? <hi>be Zealous therefore and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> So then if God, and that out of his love, doe afflict his ſervants, going aſtray for their profit, that they might pertake of his holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what doth this hinder but that they repenting and beleeving, may have that judgement or puniſhment, remooved from them, ſeeing God upon their humiliation and faith, doth promiſe it, and is <hi>grieved for their miſery,</hi> Iudg. 10.16.</p>
               <p>Concerning your ſecond caſe of probation and tryall, wherein you endeavour to ſhut abſolute prayer from the view of men, it is nothing at all againſt it, for thoſe in Heb. 11.37. ſuffered thoſe things for the truth ſake, neither did they <hi>accept deliverance.</hi> And Paul alſo 2. Cor. 11.37. ſuffered thoſe things for the Goſpels ſake in time of perſecution, as he teſtifieth 2. Tim. 1.12. which kind of ſufferings, both of Paul and thoſe in the Hebrew, <hi>are bleſſings,</hi> and the portions of Gods ſervants, not to be prayed againſt, but rather rejoyced in, unto the partaking of which afflictions, Paul exhorteth Timothy in the chapter before quoted.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>8</label> Now that neither of theſe caſes doe proove the temporall promiſes to be conditionall, or contradict ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute prayer for temporall neceſſaries, it is plaine, and you may ſee it further prooved in that which we have ſayd in defence of that Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, unto which I referre you.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7192:22"/>
               <p> SUch things as are ordinarily denyed to the beſt and moſt faithfull ſervants of God, and accompany not their condition here, cannot be abſolutely prayed for, or exſpected, neither will that procure them, for that were to croſſe his providence.</p>
               <p>But theſe outward matters are ſo as is rehearſed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This appeares by 2. teſtimonies.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames chap. 2.5. God hath choſen the poore in this world, to be rich in faith, and heires of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, rich in faith, and yet outwardly poore; the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of faith therefore helps not their poverty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of our Saviour Math. 25.35. I was hungry, and ye fed me not, thirſty, and ye gave me no drinke, naked, and ye cloathed me not, &amp;c. wherein it appeares that ſome of the members of Chriſt ſhall be poore and diſtreſſed, wanting neceſſaries in all times to the end of the world, neither are theſe taxed for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of faith at all, nor yet doth the Lord faile of any of his promiſes to his ſervants, much leſſe by a continuall courſe, therefore are they denyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the ſecond Argument.</head>
               <p>TO this I anſwer, that the Minor propoſition is alſo falſe, for whereas you ſay, outward neceſſary things are <hi>ordinaryly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to the best of Gods ſervants, and that they accompany not their condition,</hi> it is no ſuch matter. Firſt, outward neceſſaries (unleſſe in caſe of their fayling and diſobedience, or when they are deprived of them for the Goſpels ſake in caſe of perſecution, which is a bleſſed thing, and their portion, againſt which they have no warrant to pray, as wee have elſewhere declared) are not ordinaryly denyed the Saints, for David in all his obſervations never found it ſo, as his owne words doe witneſſe, <hi>I have bene young, and now am old,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.35</note> 
                  <hi>yet have I not ſeene the righteous forſaken, nor their ſeed begging bread;</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:7192:23"/>and the Pſalmiſt doth give the reaſon,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſ. </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>Thoſe that waite upon the Lord, ſhall inherit the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly that theſe outward neceſſaries doe accompany the condition of the Saints here, (contrary to your aſſertion) its plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prooved. All was loſt in Adam, but reſtored againe to thoſe, (and to thoſe onely) who are renewed in Chriſt Ieſus, and to them of right it doth belong by vertue of the promiſe; all the reſt are but uſurpers. Wherefore ſaith the Prophet, <hi>If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the Land.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay.</hi> 1.19.</note> Which promiſe is confirmed by our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſsed are the meeke, for they ſhall inherit the earth.</hi> Poſſeſſe God in Chriſt, and in Chriſt ye ſhall poſſeſſe all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, if thou thy ſelf be not wanting to God.</p>
               <p>Concerning thoſe 2 places which you alledge for prooving your owne tenent, and for confuting of ours, they ſerve not to performe either. For whereas you ſay repeatingly from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames, <hi>That God hath choſen the poore in this world, to be rich in faith.</hi> Wee deny it not, neither doth it make againſt us, for we affirme that the Saints muſt not looke after great matters, after riches and bravery, but they having <hi>meat and rayment, let them be therewithall content.</hi> And if they will not be content with this, but deſire greater matters, no marvaill if they pray <hi>conditionally,</hi> ſeeing God promiſed them no more. And how can this proove the promiſes to be conditionall? <hi>The Saints of God are many times poore;</hi> Ergo <hi>the promiſes doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a condition.</hi> How doth this hang together? I leave it to your owne judgement.</p>
               <p>Wee ſay not that poverty is to be prayed againſt, for ſo long as the <hi>barrell of meale waſteth not, and the cruſe of oyle faileth not,</hi> tis as much as can be deſired; but if <hi>our meat wasteth, and our oyle fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> wee impute the cauſe to our fayling: Faith and repentance may help that, although not poverty. Concerning your ſecond teſtimony, that our Saviour Math. 25. <hi>I was hungrie, and ye fed me not, &amp;c.</hi> whence you ſay, <hi>that it appeares that ſome of the members of Christ ſhall be poore and diſtreſſed, wanting neceſsaries in all times to the end of the world.</hi> Put caſe this be graunted, what is it to the purpoſe? many of the Saints ſay you, ſhall want neceſſaries; Ergo the promiſes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a condition: Or what will you conclude? muſt we not therefore pray abſolute? If we ſhould take this place literally, as you doe, to ſerve your owne turne, wee muſt needs conclude from the former
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7192:23"/>verſes, that all the Saints that either were, are, or ſhall be, never wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but had ſome overplus to help others: for our Saviour witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth (for he ſpeakes to all the Saints in generall) that they were all feeders, all cloathers, all viſiters of others. So then I underſtand that of our Saviour from verſe the 34. to the 41. to declare the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable communion, help and comfort, which the Saints of all degrees doe adminiſter one to another, which is an abſolute proofe that they are all the ſervants of God, becauſe <hi>they love one another.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which you urge from verſ. 41. <hi>ad finem,</hi> I conceive it thus; Our Saviour in thoſe words doth upbraid the wicked, and tells them that hee hath nothing to doe with them, and that they ſhall miſſe of their ayme; for (as if hee had ſayd) <hi>You denied me before men, and now I denie you: You ſhewed no kindneſse of me in my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and now I will ſhew you none: You ſaw my members perſecuted for the truth, and put in priſon, &amp;c. but you did not (as your duetie was) comfort, relieve and viſit them, but rather if I was but a little angrie, you helped forward their affliction: You love not theſe my ſonnes, which were begotten, and your ſelves must needs confeſse, you cannot love him that begetteth, out of your owne mouthes I will condemne you, (what need we anie more witneſse?) Abite maledicti, &amp;c.</hi> Iudge righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement, wherein doth this proove the temporall promiſes to be conditionall? or confute abſolute prayer for them?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice <hi>his third Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which never did put any certain difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene one and another, in outward things, is not the abſolute condition of thoſe things, for that cannot ſtand:</p>
               <p>But faith and grace did never put any certain diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene one and another in outward things; Ergo is not the condition, nor annexed to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This appeares by 2. places.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Eccleſ. 9.2. All things come alike unto all, and there is one event to him that feareth God, and to him that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him not, &amp;c. and no man knowes love or hatred, by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7192:24"/>all that is before him, verſ. 1. which would not be ſo, if there were any certain bettering of the outward eſtate by faith and grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Math. 5.45. Your heavenly Father maketh his ſunne to riſe on the evill and on the good: and ſendeth raine on the juſt and unjuſt: ſo that the very ſame diſpenſation in outward things, belongs to one as to another, and there is no difference, which providence doth interpret the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes concerning theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the third Argument.</head>
               <p>TO this Argument I muſt anſwer as to the former <hi>negando,</hi> by denying your <hi>Minor,</hi> and that juſtly too; for <hi>Faith &amp; Grace have put a certaine difference betweene one and another, and betweene their posteritie too;</hi> as the Scriptures doe plentifully witneſſe. Hee bleſſeth the ſeede of the faithfull in outward things, for the integrity of their parents, and plagues the ſeed of the wicked with outward puniſhments, for the ſinnes of their fathers. To this purpoſe read the ſecond commandement, and compare that of the Proverbs with that of the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.16.</note> 
                  <hi>The juſt man walketh in his integritie, his children are bleſsed after him. But the face of the Lord is against them that doe evill, to cut off the remembrance of them from off the earth.</hi> See Proverbs 10.7. and compare that of the Pſalmiſt 102.28. with Pſal. 37.28.34. and with that of Iob 21.19. and then tell me (and tell me truely) whether <hi>faith and grace did never put any certaine difference betweene one and another in outward things?</hi> The wicked (it is true) <hi>may flouriſh like a bay-tree for a while,</hi> but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faith and grace, they are quickly gone; a man may <hi>ſeeke them, but ſhall not find them;</hi> but faith and grace doe eſtabliſh the juſt. Peruſe the 37. Pſalm from the beginning to the end, and it will plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare. And we ſee by experience, how mercifully the Lord doth deale with the poſterity of thoſe, who doe walke in uprightneſſe; and how hee doth bring to nothing in a ſmall time, the great reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of thoſe who are profane and enimies to piety.</p>
               <p>Concerning thoſe 2 places which you produce to proove your poſition, you doe greatly miſtake the meaning of the holy Ghoſt in them; for the meaning of the holy Ghoſt in that of Eccl. 9.1.2. is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7192:24"/>quite contrary to your interpretation, for your interpretation is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the judgement of the world, which judgement the holy Ghoſt doth condemne, as appeareth verſ. 3. for (ſaith hee) this is an evill among all things that are done under the ſunne. Men of the world judge it ſo; But what then? Becauſe they ſay there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the juſt and the unjuſt, concerning theſe things, muſt their ſayings therefore be true? Alas it is no ſuch matter. For the Lord doth ſharpely reproove all thoſe, who doe ſay that faith and grace doe put no certaine difference in this life, concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things betweene one and another. For he ſaith that ſuch words are <hi>ſtout words against him,</hi> as appeareth Mal. 3.13.14.15. verſes, for ſaith the Lord, <hi>Your words have bene ſtout against me:</hi> But the people ſayd, <hi>What have we ſpoken ſo much againſt thee?</hi> Unto which queſtion the Lord made this anſwer, <hi>Ye have ſayd it is in vaine to ſerve God, &amp;c. and now we call the proud happie; Yea they that worke wickedneſſe are ſet up, yea they that tempt God, are even delivered.</hi> For this purpoſe ſee Iob 21.15.</p>
               <p>To ſay that faith and grace doe make no difference betweene one and another in outward things, is wee ſee to ſpeake proudly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. David (wee muſt confeſſe) was almoſt perſwaded that his faith and grace had put no certaine difference betweene him, and the wicked, in outward things (for he ſayd, <hi>I have cleanſed my heart in vaine</hi>) untill he went into the Sanctuary of God, but then he found a difference, as is prooved verſ. 37. yea and that a plaine difference too <hi>betweene him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond place that you alleadge to proove your aſſertion, is in Math. 5.45. <hi>Your heavenlie Father maketh his ſunne to ſhine, &amp;c.</hi> whence you ſay that the <hi>verie ſame diſpenſation in outward things, belongs to one as to another.</hi> You ſay it indeed, but you have not prooved it, neither can you proove it by the Word of God. For (which indeed doth put a ſpeciall difference betweene one and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other) there is a ſpeciall difference in the diſpenſation of outward things. It is true, the Lord out of his abundant goodneſſe, doth give gifts and bleſſings to all, to the juſt and unjuſt, but ſuch bleſſings doe not (as you ſay) <hi>belong to all.</hi> They belong to the juſt onely, becauſe they are promiſed onely to them, even ſo many as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by Chriſt Ieſus. God hath given to them Chriſt, and with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7192:25"/>him all other outward neceſſaries, and by vertue of his promiſes, they may chalenge them to be theirs. And the Lord gives it them by promiſe. Now the Lord doth give the wicked many bleſſings, but not by promiſe. Neither can any wicked man gather any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe out of the Word of God, as that the leaſt favour belongs unto him. And hence it is that it is generally received for truth, that the wicked have all they have, not for their owne, but for the righteous ſakes. For were it not for them, the wicked ſhould all ſuddenly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. The Lord would in a moment, as Iob ſayth, <hi>cauſe them to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 20.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and caſt it out of their bellyes.</hi> So that wee ſee theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things are diverſly diſpenſed upon the ſonnes of God, and the Imps of the devill. The Lord gives them to the Saints as hee gave <hi>Abraham his ſonne Iſaac</hi> by <hi>promiſe,</hi> but hee gives them to the wicked, as he gave <hi>Abraham Iſmaell,</hi> not by <hi>promiſe.</hi> The manner of which diſpenſation doth quite overthrow your tenent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice <hi>his fourth Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which the Lord Ieſus and his Apoſtles did pray for, or againſt conditionally, is ſo to be done of us, for wee are bid to follow their examples, and to try our ſpirits and practiſes by theirs, and not theirs by ours. But our Lord and his Apoſtles did ſo. Ergo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This is prooved by two places.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Luk. 22.42. Father if thou be willing, let this cup paſſe from me, yet not my will, but thine be done: Here is the deprecation of an outward evill, not abſolutely, but with ſubmiſſion to the will of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Rom. 1.10. Making requeſt, if by any meanes I might have a proſperous journey by the will of God to come to you. Here is an outward benefit, yea ſomewhat more (ſeeing it was a ſervice to the Church) deſired with ſubmiſſion to Gods will. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames layes downe a rule for all to follow in ſuch caſes, ye ought to ſay, if God will, Iames 4.15. What is it then to teach, that wee ought
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7192:25"/>not to ſay, if the Lord will, but directly to croſſe the word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the fourth Argument.</head>
               <p>IN this Argument I deny your Major propoſition, a doctrine more fit to be ſpewed out, then to be taught in the Church of Chriſt, being (as was your firſt propoſition) a chief pillar of the Church of Rome. This we will make plainely to appeare. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is mans duety to obſerve in Gods ſervice, that muſt be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God, for nothing but a commandement from God, can make a man owe a duety to God. This appeares by that expres ſaying of the Preacher, where hee doth clearely proove,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13</note> that all mans duety unto God is contayned in commaundements (precepts being the true ground of dueties) for ſaith hee, <hi>feare God and keepe his commaundements, for this is the whole of man, or the whole duetie of man.</hi> This is ſeconded by our Saviour, when hee was to leave his Diſciples; for the commiſſion which Chriſt gave his Diſciples run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thus, <hi>Goe teach all nations, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20</note> 
                  <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commaunded you.</hi> Upon which commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Calvine in his Harmony upon the Euangeliſts, ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Christ ſendeth forth his Apoſtles with this exception, that they thrust not to men their owne inventions, but that they doe purelie and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie dispence from hand to hand (as it were) that which he himſelf hath commaunded. And I would to God, the Pope would ſubmit the right, which he arrogateth to himſelf to this rule, &amp;c. But he infecteth the Church with his owne trifles, &amp;c.</hi> Now if any man ſhall teach men to obſerve any thing as a duety, which God hath not <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> tis beyond his commiſſion; a created worſhip, a worſhip of his owne invention, which God never required.</p>
               <p>Now whereas you make examples without the authority of any commaundement, to be the ground of a duety, what is it els but (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>to beguile men of their reward in a voluntarie hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,</hi> (.i.) in will-worſhip, which is <hi>Idolatrie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18.</note> Now you ſay (for the confirmation of your <hi>Major</hi>) that we are bid to follow their axamples. Quote that Scripture that biddeth or commaundeth us to follow their examples in praying <hi>conditionallie for outward neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> and we will lay our hands upon our mouthes. Sure I am Chriſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7192:26"/>did checke this kind of praying, but I find not where he doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund it.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 22.9</note> Theſe words repeated by you <hi>(we are bid to follow their examples)</hi> I thinke you take them from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peter, <hi>leaving us an example</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that we ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21</note> Hee doth not wiſh us to follow his ſteps in every thing that hee did, (for although every action of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles is written for our inſtruction, it followeth not that therefore it is written for our imitation) but <hi>patiently to ſuffer for well-doing,</hi> which was the thing handled in that place by the Apoſtle, and in other places commaunded: which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, not any example, is the ground of the duety. Wee confeſſe the ſpirits of the Prophets muſt be ſubject to the Prophets, (.i.) our ſpirits and practiſes muſt be ſubject to their doctrine: And for this we earneſtly contend. You would make their practiſes our rules, but wee make their doctrine our rules, both for doctrine and practiſes.</p>
               <p>Concerning your Minor propoſition, if we deny not, but grant that our Saviour and his Apoſtles did pray as you ſay, yet we deny that their examples in that particular ought to be our rule. As for thoſe two places,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.24 <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10.</note> you alledge the one of our Saviour, and that of Paul, it ſhall not be unmeete to ſay ſome thing of them, to ſhew your unadviſedneſſe, that you would from theſe ſayings fetch in an <hi>If,</hi> into the fourth petition of the Lords Prayer; for that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Luke 22.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 14.36.</note> Father if thou be willing, let this cup paſſe from me. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Marke hath it thus without any condition, Abba Father, all things are poſſible to thee, take away this cup from me. Here he prayeth without an <hi>If,</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Luke with an
<note n="*" place="margin">The Greek word it, is taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for foraſmuch as, and ſo it agrees with that of Marke.</note> 
                  <hi>If.</hi> What doth let but (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your argument) that we may affirme, that we muſt pray ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, as well as you ſay, we ought to pray conditionally for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things? but wee have a more firme foundation to build on, then upon examples to ground dueties, as we have declared. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this prayer of Chriſt, Calvine is of this opinion, that this prayer of Chriſt was not a premeditated prayer (<hi>ſed vis &amp; impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp;c.</hi> but the force and violence of grief, did extort from him thoſe words, to the which he added by and by a correction, Not as I will. As alſo another writer ſayth of theſe words: It was nothing then the complaint of a mind, toyling and diſtreſſed; <hi>(&amp; nequaquam just a precatio fuit, etſi oratio vera fuit)</hi> and not a juſt forme of praying, although it might be true prayer. Chriſt knew full well that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7192:26"/>hee muſt needs dye, to worke our redemption, for hee came for that purpoſe, as hee himſelf doth acknowledge. It was the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Fathers anger, and the horribleneſſe of the puniſhment, due unto all our ſinnes, that did even retaine for a time the whole humane mind, and extracted this pittyfull complaint from him. But after the power of his Divinity, rayſed him up, hee ſpake after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other manner, as Mathew witneſſeth, for he introduceth him, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus: Oh Father, ſeeing this cup cannot paſſe from me, but I muſt drinke it, thy will be done. I beſeech you now, conſider well what warrant is there by theſe words of Chriſt, to thruſt an <hi>If</hi> into the fourth petition of the Lords prayer? Eſpecially ſeeing this of Chriſt is rather to be referred unto the ſixt petition, hee fighteth againſt temptations. Now if you thruſt an <hi>If</hi> into the ſixt, why then not alſo into the fift? And then notwithſtanding any gloſſe its all Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. That of Paul to the Romans doth ſhew the deſire he had to come unto them, to impart ſome ſpirituall gift, but he had no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, that hee ſhould come unto them, and therefore it is no marvaill, ſeeing hee put in an <hi>If.</hi> And when any one doe deſire any thing, which God hath not promiſed, hee muſt needs put in an <hi>If,</hi> for ſure it is, hee can have no certain aſſurance; hee may well doubt of enjoying the things deſired.</p>
               <p>Now whereas you ſay, that <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. James layes downe a rule, &amp;c.</hi> If you ſay S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames layes downe that rule for all to follow in praying for temporall neceſſaries, you doe groſſely abuſe the meaning of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames; for he doth not there ſpeake of prayer, but did ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove all thoſe, who did peremptorily ſay, <hi>Wee will goe to ſuch a citty, and continue there a yeare or two, and get gaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.14 <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15.</note> when as they had no promiſe to live one houre, as hee ſpeaketh; whereupon hee inferreth this ſaying, <hi>for that ye ought to ſay, if the Lord will wee ſhall live to doe this or that.</hi> No man knoweth whether hee ſhall live one day (for ought any one know the day of judgement may be before to morrow) and therefore they may be juſtly reprooved and condemned for vaine boaſters, who ſay (notwithſtanding they have no promiſe to live a day) <hi>that they will goe to any place to buy and ſell two or three yeares, and get gaine.</hi> Now whether or no this rule of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames be a rule for us, to pray by for temporall neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, let the wiſe and diſcreet judge. Laſtly from theſe words of yours <hi>(what is it then to teach that we ought not to ſay, If the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:7192:27"/>will, but directlie to croſſe the Word of God.)</hi> I can collect nothing but this: That you <hi>ſpeake evill of that which you understand not, and know not whereof you affirme,</hi> for you are come from praying to ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As if there was no difference betweene them? Enough of that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice <hi>his fift Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the faith of miracles was limited, and bounded by the will of God, then all other faith is ſo:</p>
               <p>But the faith of miracles was confined to the will of God, and his pleaſure. Ergo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This appeares.</head>
               <p n="1">1. By Acts 19.12. where it is plaine, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul had the faith of miracles, and healed diſeaſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet 2. Timoth. 4.20. hee complaints that hee left Trophimus at Miletum ſick. No doubt but he did deſire his health, and prayed for it, but could not obtaine it, though it be promiſed that the prayer of faith ſhall heale the ſicke, Iam. 5.15. becauſe it is ſubject to Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and will, which ſhewes the promiſes to be condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall.</p>
               <p>Q. If any aſke then how we ſhall pray in faith for any outward thing, if it be uncertaine whether wee ſhall have them.</p>
               <p>A. I anſwer, wee beleeve that wee ſhall have whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is good for us, which the Lord beſt knoweth, either the outward benefit, or grace to ſupply it, as 2. Corinth. 12.9.</p>
               <p>Obj. If any object, that wee may pray abſolutely for things neceſſary, as wee may to doe the will of God, and that his name may be glorified by us, ſeeing ſuch things conduce thereunto.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:7192:27"/>
               <p> Sol. I reply that the will of God is done, and his will glorifyed, as well by our paſſive as by our active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in ſuffering quietly his pleaſure and will, and hath the like reward, Ioh. 21.19. Iames 1.12.</p>
               <p>The contrary opinion then is a ſpeaking of God and of his adminiſtration, that which is not right, which kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his wrath againſt his owne ſervants, Iob 42.7.</p>
               <p>It is a limiting and confining of his workes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to mens wils and deſires; a praying againſt all his corrections, and tryall utterly.</p>
               <p>It is a condemning of the eſtate of the righteous, and a ſadding of thoſe that ought to be comforted, a ſtrayning of the promiſes beyond their intendement, and the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of a preſumptuous and unwarrantable kind of praying.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>EDW. NORRICE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the fift Argument.</head>
               <p>TO this argument I thus anſwer, that (if by the will of God you underſtand his revealed will) wee deny not but that faith is limited and bounded by the will of God, revealed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (.i.) faith is bounded by the promiſes of God, which are the ground of faith. Neither doth this in any meaſure contradict our te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, or proove what you affirme. But if by the will of God you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that will, whereof you are ignorant, as it ſeemes you doe, by that which you have ſayd, (.i.) if you bound faith with Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and not with his revealed will onely, I utterly deny your whole Argument; for both the faith of miracles, and all other faith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 19.12</note> have no other bound, or ground, but the revealed will of God; his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. And that faith of miracles, and healing diſeaſes, which Paul had, was bounded with, and grounded onely upon the promiſes. For what the Apoſtle did in working miracles and curing diſeaſes, hee had the authority of an abſolute promiſe, as it appeareth Ioh. 14.12. <hi>Verely, Verely,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I ſay unto you, hee that beleeveth on me, the works which I doe ſhall hee doe, and greater workes then theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7192:28"/>ſhall hee doe, becauſe I goe to the Father.</hi> Now whereas you goe about to nullify this promiſe, and to proove from that of Paul to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.20.</note> that the promiſes are conditionall, becauſe (as you ſay) <hi>Paul had the gift of healing, but could not cure Trophimus, that was ſicke,</hi> I anſwer that all you ſay herein is as nothing; for (ſay you) <hi>Paul left Trophimus at Miletum ſicke.</hi> Whence you alſo ſay, <hi>No doubt, but hee deſired his health, and prayed for it, but could not obtaine it. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> where is your evidence to proove this? or who told you that Paul prayed for his health, and could not obtaine it? Where is this prooved in the Scriptures?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29</note> The <hi>ſecret things</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe to the Lord our God: But thoſe things which are revealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and to our children for ever.</hi> This is not (for ought I find) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and therefore it is not for you to determine. You ſay (and but ſay it) no doubt hee prayed for him; another may ſay, no doubt hee did not pray for him; a third may ſay, no doubt hee tould Paul, that hee had finiſhed his courſe, and would not have him to pray for his life; a fourth may ſay, no doubt but hee recovered after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and was healed. Now which of you ſhall a man beleeve? or who ſhall decide the caſe, and tell us which of theſe doubts is true? Truely (for my part) I know not how it can be rightly reſolved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you can call Paul or Trophimus from the dead againe. Strange and lamentable then it is, that you would goe about to drawe a concluſion, to proove your aſſertion from that which is ſo uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, nay (which is more) by ſuppoſitions, and ſuch uncertain col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, to contradict commaundements, and to goe about to nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify promiſes. And to ſpeake truth, all your Arguments doe tend to this one end, namely, to contradict a commandement, or nullify promiſes: And what is this els, but to contend againſt the truth? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view with a ſingle eye your owne proceedings in theſe your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and you may plainely ſee, that they are bent againſt the truth; for the drift of them is to eſtabliſh a will-worſhip, a duety which God never commanded: It is to pray conditionally for temporall neceſſaries. For <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> where is your commandement to proove ſuch a duety? as alſo they doe oppoſe commandements, and bend their forces to alter the nature of the promiſes. But they looſe their labour, for <hi>cedunt arma togae,</hi> away with Arguments (blunt weapons) when commandements (ſharp ſwords) come in place; for it may be ſayd of them, as (in another caſe) it was ſayd of old,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7192:28"/>
                  <hi>One commandement ſhall chaſe a thouſand arguments, and two put tenn thouſand to flight.</hi> What now remaineth, but that you confeſſe your errour (for its cleare you have erred) and give them ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which you have made to erre by your Arguments. And as you have taught men to obſerve, that which Chriſt never commanded, ſo now teach the contrary, which is, what Chriſt hath commanded. Neither is it (to uſe your owne words) <hi>any diſgrace for any man to revoke an errour, but his praiſe and glory, and the testimony of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious mind, and of the feare of God.</hi> Thus have I now by Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance (contrary to your conceit) ſayd ſome thing to that which you have ſayd, and as you requeſted me ſet downe, wherein your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are faulty and fayling.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you (ſeeing it was your owne deſire that I ſhould ſend you word, wherein they were faulty and failing) that you would not take any paſſage in this my anſwer, in the worſt part, or imagine, I ſpeake any thing to vent cholere, or to diſparidge you: but rather receive it (as I write it in defence of the truth) in love, and love ſhall cover all offences. And in concluſion, I pray you take notice: That it is your opinion, that is a ſpeaking of God, and of his adminiſtration, that which is not right, which kindleth his wrath againſt his owne ſervants, it cauſeth men to arrogate to themſelves too much,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 42.7.</note> and to give to God too little. It is a perverting of the promiſes, beſide their intendement, and the teaching of an ignorant and unwarrantable kind of praying.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:7192:29"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice his PROSOPOPEIA.</head>
            <head type="sub">A draught of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice his collections from certain paſſages and writings, which hee ſent about the Country, affirming them to be the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Rice Boye,</hi> ſet downe under his owne hand, and in his owne name, as in and by the ſaid draught here following it doth and may appeare.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FIRST PART.</head>
               <p>A View of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Boys</hi> aſſertions, ſet downe under his owne hand, and in his owne name, and ſome others, concerning the point of abſolute praying for temporall bleſſings in the particulars, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any condition, expreſſed or implyed of the will of God therein, or of our owne everlaſting good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to this first Part.</head>
               <p>THat the Reader without all <hi>If,</hi> ſhould both conſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and report, that <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> hath related no more from my writings, but what he receaved, he preſents (as he ſayth in the firſt place) to his view no more, but <hi>a view of my aſsertions, ſet downe under my owne hand, and that concerning the point of abſolute praying for temporall bleſſings, &amp;c.</hi> wherein <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> doth cunningly play the Sophiſter, even ſlyly poſſeſſe the Reader with a bad conceit of my aſſertions, before ever he hath heard or ſeene them; as appeareth, firſt in that he uſeth the word <hi>bleſſings,</hi> indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, whereas I uſe them definitely of ſuch bleſſings, as God hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7192:29"/>commaunded us to aſke, and promiſed to give. And ſecondly (which is worſt of all) in that he doth uſe theſe words, <hi>in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars without any condition, expreſſed of the will of God therein;</hi> whereas they are words of his owne addition and invention; for in all my writings there is no ſuch matter written. Whereby he would needs (as farre as I can gather) poſſeſſe the Reader with theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: Firſt, <hi>that I ſhould teach men to pray abſolutely for all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſings whatſoever:</hi> And not onely ſo, but that in the ſecond place I ſhould <hi>tye God to bestow upon us what we pleaſe, without any relation to Gods revealed will, recorded in the Scriptures.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>è contra</hi> (alas miſerable it is to ſee how it is abuſed) the whole drift of my writings is to perſwade men to pray unto God for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings, according to his will revealed, or expreſſed in the Scriptures; <hi>which will of God</hi> (as in my ſaid writings tis plainely prooved, as wee ſhall hereafter cleare) <hi>ought to be the onely directrix of all our requeſts.</hi> I affirme in that which I have written, that all our petitions ought to be framed according to Gods will, expreſſed in his Word; and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> gives out, and that in writing too, that theſe are <hi>my aſsertions ſet under my owne hand, and in my owne name, concerning the point of abſolute praying for outward bleſſings in the particulars, without any condition expreſsed of the will of God therein.</hi> Sir, you have made but a bad beginning, and (as it will appeare anon) a worſe concluſion. But more of this hereafter. And thus from the Title or Preface I paſſe to his collections. And thus they follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>HE ſaith, 1. That this opinion is newly rayſed from the dead (by him and his Complices) and that it hath a long time bene buried in the pit of oblivion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That to uſe the conditionall <hi>If,</hi> (to ſtand with the will of God) in praying for any temporall benefit, doth argue both ignorance and infidelity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that we may be ſure to obtaine the very thing petitioned, if the fault be not in our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And therefore that wee ſhould not rudely, unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7192:30"/>and ignorantly, upon all occaſions, runne to God onely with an <hi>If.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. For our petitions are not then aggreeable to the will of God, when wee ſay: If it be thy will to give us this or that: neither doth the Lord delight in ſuch bablings; but when wee leave it out, and ſay: Lord thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give the thing wee now deſire at thy hands.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Neither let thy heart put thee off with this poore excuſe: The Lord doth not ſee it good for thee.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Come out then, oh thou conditionall, from among the petitions of the Lords prayer, and ſit downe yonder, for thou wert never placed there by Chriſt, nor art of his planting; thou haſt robd God of his glory, and deprived us of many bleſſings, and a long time luld us in too much ignorance and ſecurity, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That to affirme the promiſes of God for temporall things, are conditionall, is a doctrine of mans invention, one of the Popes unwritten verityes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. For that all the promiſes made to the obedient, are abſolute in Levit. 26. and Deuter. 28. ſo that if they did what was required, it was abſolute, &amp; certain they ſhould have the bleſſings, and there was no other thing mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or implyed, and ſo for the diſobedient on their parts, the evills and puniſhments, threatned in theſe outward things.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Alſo that the Saints may and ought, as abſolutely looke for temporall neceſſaries, and pray for them, as for the forgiveneſſe and pardon of the their ſinnes, &amp;c. (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Pſal. 73.)</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the Martyrs Heb. 11.37. that are ſayd not to accept deliverance, did refuſe it, becauſe perſecution is a bleſſing, and the portion of Gods people, in which they are to rejoyce, and therefore there is no warrant to pray
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7192:30"/>againſt perſecution at all, for it is to pray againſt a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, &amp;c. (ſo the Martyrs perſecuted themſelves.)</p>
               <p n="12">12. That when Salomon ſaith Eccleſ. 9.2. All things come alike to all, and there is one event, &amp;c. he ſpeaketh not as the truth is, but according to the judgement, and cenſure of the world, that doth ſo thinke and imagine, and therefore in the third verſe the holy Ghoſt doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, ſaying, it is an evill he ſaw under the ſunne; that is, that men ſay there is no difference betweene good &amp; bad in outward things, but all things come alike, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="13">13 That to teach men to follow the example of our Saviour Chriſt and the Apoſtles (even in this matter of prayer and ſubmiſſion to the will of God) is a doctrine worthy to be ſpued out of the Church, and not fit to be taught therein; for that we are to follow rules, and not the example of any, therefore thô our Saviour and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul did (as we confeſſe) pray conditionally for outward mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet wee are not to follow them, nor to make their doings our rule, it being a chief pillar of the Church of Rome, this ground, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="14">14 That whereas S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames chap. 4.15. gives a charge to all that they ought to ſay, not abſolutely, but with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if the Lord will, I will doe this or that, is nothing to our purpoſe; for that is of ſaying, and this of praying.</p>
               <p n="15">15 That to ſay when Paul left Trophimus at Miletum ſicke, undoubtedly he deſired his health, and prayed for him, is an unwarrantable ſpeech and groundleſſe colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for who told you S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul prayed for his health, or where is it revealed in Scripture? and therefore another may ſay, no doubt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul did not pray for his health, &amp;c. for my part I cannot ſee how it ſhould be reſolved, unles wee call Paul or Trophimus from the dead againe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="16">16 That for any to teach men to pray conditionally
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7192:31"/>for temporall benefits, and with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed or implyed, is to blaſpheme the truth, and to teach an ignorant and unfaithfull kinde of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Concord. cum Originali.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Anſwer to this ſecond Part.</head>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Norrice</hi> having laid downe his Preface, in the next place be layeth downe the particular aſſertions of his owne colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from my writing, but ſitting them (for the moſt part) to make good his conceits concerning them, that ſo there might be ſome ſhew of honeſtie in his proceedings. And therefore to make good his reports, in the firſt place he ſetteth downe a preface, pretending it to be the ground of my opinion, concerning praying for outward things. And to make that ſeeme apparant, hee doth in the next place by an idle Proſopopeia faine me ſpeaking to his purpoſe; for (ſaith hee) hee ſaith, that is <hi>Rice Boye</hi> ſaith theſe and theſe things. So that the Reader muſt neceſſarily underſtand, that <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> doth bring me in ſpeaking thus: <hi>I Rice Boye doe ſay that this opinion is newly rayſed from the dead, &amp;c.</hi> Now what I have ſayd, and what he ſayth (good Reader) thou ſhalt plainely ſee. And that wee may proceed orderly, and omit nothing, I will ſpeake particularly of each particular as they lye in order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt thing collected in my writings is thus written: <hi>And that which wee ſpeake is no uncouth and novell opinion (as ſome judge it) for we have delivered no more, but what we have received: Moſes taught it to the Iſraelits, Christ to his Apostles, his Apoſtles to their Congregations, and wee doe but rayſe that from the dead, which a longe time hath laien buried in the pit of oblivion.</hi> Herein I gave you to underſtand, that what I held in prayer was no <hi>novell opinion,</hi> but the ſame as Moſes, Chriſt, the Apoſtles and other godly Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore maintained; and that I and my <hi>Complices</hi> (ſo you ſay, thô by a parentheſis of your owne thruſting in) <hi>did but raiſe that from the dead,</hi> that is, (you could not be ignorant of my meaning before) we did but ſpeake of that which you and your <hi>Complices</hi> kept, and ſtill labour to keepe buried in the pit of oblivion. And I pray you what was that we thus ſpoke of? was it not this? <hi>That all our prayers ought
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7192:31"/>to be framed according to Gods will, expreſſed in his Word, and that all ſuch prayers</hi> (yea for outward neceſſaries) <hi>were to be made abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to God, without doubting and wavering, &amp;c.</hi> as in the title of my ſayd writings is expreſſed. This was that opinion whereof I was, and continue ſtill defendant. But you devulge about the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that I and ſome others have rayſed from the dead this opinion; namely, an opinion concerning <hi>abſolute praying for outward bleſsings without relation to the will of God, revealed or expreſſed in his word.</hi> Have you done well in this? I appeale to your ſelf for judgement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond place in my writing is thus: <hi>Which manner of praying doth manifeſt both ignorance and infidelity: wee know not whether it be the will of God or not, to give us ſuch things as we aſke, and then no marvaill if we doubt whether we ſhall obtaine them yea or no.</hi> A little before having ſhewed the nature of the word <hi>If,</hi> I aſked this queſtion: <hi>In what ſence is this word If, uſed in prayer for outward things? as it is conditionall or doubtfull?</hi> (for ſo is <hi>If</hi> taken) <hi>if conditionall, then</hi> (ſayd I) <hi>our prayers for outward neceſsary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings muſt be framed thus: Oh Father, if the gift of things neceſſary for my preſent being ſhall ſtand with thy will, then be pleaſed to beſtow it upon me. In which petition this word If, is not onely conditionall, but alſo doubtfull: Wee doe not by this ſaying referre it to the will of God, but in ſo praying wee doubt whether it doth agree with the will of God, to beſtow upon us things neceſsary for our preſent being.</hi> By this I make it plaine, how and in what manner this word <hi>If,</hi> doth manifeſt both <hi>ignorance and infidelity</hi> in prayer. But this you leape over, and urge ſome of that which follows (mingling it with ſome of your owne) as a dangerous doctrine. And I pray you Sir, what errour is there, in ſaying, that <hi>If,</hi> as it is a note, not onely of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but alſo of doubt, doth manifeſt both ignorance and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſeeing when wee ſo pray, wee thereby confeſſe, that wee know not whether it be the will of God or not, to give us ſuch things as wee aſke. And if wee are ignorant of Gods will, concerning the thing wee aſke, no marvaill if we doubt whether we ſhall obtaine it, yea or no. It had bene well if you had preſented to the Readers view the full grounds of my writings; but it ſeemes you feared to unfold too much: for why els doe you in ſo many particulars cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile my ſayings?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third place is thus in my writings: <hi>Call now to minde our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7192:32"/>former grounds, and this alſo will unreſistably follow: The fault is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine at the hands of God the very thing pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned.</hi> A little before I layd downe five things, which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily required in prayer, which I wiſh the Reader to call to mind. The five particulars (as you ſhall find them written) are theſe: Firſt when we pray we muſt come to God with holy hands. Secondly without wrath. Thirdly without doubting. Theſe 3 are recorded by the Apoſtle 1. Timoth. 2.8. Fourthly we muſt aſke for the true ends, not to conſume it on our luſts, Iam. 4.3. Fiftly wee muſt aſke what we doe aſke according to his will, 1. Ioh. 5.14. Theſe (eſpecially) were the grounds which I wiſhed you to call to mind, and then (thoſe grounds being rightly conſidered) this alſo, I ſayd, would follow: The fault is in themſelves, who doe not obtaine at the hands of God the very thing petitioned. They faile (as the words imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly follow) in one of theſe particulars; either they know not the plague in their owne hearts, or els they faile in the duety of charity (ſo that as Chriſt ſaith Math. 11.25.) they forgive not when they pray, &amp;c. Now what danger is there in any thing, which I have here ſpoken? Doe not the Scriptures teach it? Make then your qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the word, and not with mee. But to bring a darkneſſe upon that which I have written, you have left out the ground upon which this ſaying was ſpoken, as alſo thoſe things following, which ſerve to make it plaine; and here you have ſo cunningly ſet downe this collection, as that the Reader can not conceave, but that I affirme, a man may pray for any thing, and have it. And ſurely through your words and writings together, it is generally blowne about the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that <hi>Boye</hi> affirmeth, wee may pray for any thing, and be ſure to have it; as namely for better victualls, better cloathes, more meanes and great livings, &amp;c. Alas, alas! could <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> with a good conſcience draw from my writings any coulourable ſhew for ſuch rumours? Eſpecially ſeeing it was a ſpeciall thing I perſwaded men unto, even to frame their petitions unto God, according to his will revealed in his word? That is, (as I explaned my ſelf) I would have them aſke of God, what hee had eommaunded, and beleeve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave that which hee hath promiſed. But what will not many men doe to cover their owne fayling?</p>
               <p n="4.5">4.5. The fourth and fift places are in my writings thus: Now our petitions for outward things are agreeable to Gods will, not when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7192:32"/>wee put in this word <hi>If,</hi> as to ſay, if it be thy will to give us this or that; but they are agreeable to his will, when the thing wee deſire God to beſtow upon us, is both commaunded and promiſed. This is that which doth make our petitions agreeable to his will. And therefore when wee are to pray, either for any favour, or for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooving of any affliction, wee muſt conſider with our ſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be within the compaſſe of this rule; namely, whether God in his word doth commaund us to aſke ſuch a thing which we deſire to have, and whether hee doth promiſe upon our calling, to beſtow it upon us; and not rudely and unadviſedly, nay ignorantly, upon all occaſions runne to God onely with an <hi>If.</hi> Hence it is when the Saints doe come to the Throne of grace, and ſollicite God in Ieſus Chriſt for any favour, that the holy Ghoſt doth put them upon that iſſue, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> produce your evidence; where have I commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you in the Scripture to aſke of mee ſuch or ſuch a bleſſing? where is your warrant? Where in my Scriptures have I made any ſuch contract, any ſuch covenant, any ſuch promiſe to give you ſuch or ſuch a thing, which ye deſire of me? Now if the Saints ſo praying, are able to produce their evidence, and ſay unto the Lord, Loe, here is our warrant; thou haſt commaunded us in thy word to aſke this thing, which wee now deſire, and therefore in obedience to thy commaund, wee have this boldneſſe to come unto thee: And loe, Oh Lord, (pointing as it were with the finger to the place) here is our evidence: In thy Scriptures thou haſt made a contract, a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a promiſe to give us the things wee now deſire. If I ſay, the Saints can thus anſwer the Spirit, and produce their evidence, as aforeſaid, their petition is lawfull, and they may lawfully charge God with his promiſe, his contract, his covenant. But then when the ſpirit of God puts them to that iſſue, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi libellus,</hi> produce your evidence for what ye aſke, and they are not able to produce any, either commaundement, or promiſe, deducted from his Scriptures, hee may (as one ſaith) juſtly plead and anſwer ſuch petitioners with a <hi>Non est factum,</hi> I made no ſuch promiſe. Wherefore when men pray unto God for ſuch things, as have no ground from his word, (notwithſtanding they thruſt in an <hi>If</hi>) they ſhall be ſent away empty; the Lord will plead to ſuch petitioners, <hi>Non est factum,</hi> I made no ſuch promiſe: Hee delighteth not in ſuch babling. In this long ſpeech (I could not but repeate it all) you may plainely ſee,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7192:33"/>Sir, had you read it with a ſingle eye, that which I have therein affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is no more but the truth. For firſt, a little before I demaunded this queſtion: <hi>When are our petitions agreeable with the will of God?</hi> Which queſtion is there thus anſwered: Our petitions are agreeable to the will of God, when they are agreeable to his word. Now (ſaid I) our petitions are agreeable to Gods will, not when wee put in this word <hi>If,</hi> as to ſay, if it be thy will to give us this or that; but they are agreeable to his will, when the thing we deſire God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon us, is both commaunded and promiſed. Wherein can you find this faultie, or fayling? Which of thoſe two doe make our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions agreeable to Gods will? Is it this word <hi>If,</hi> or els Gods word thinke you? What? muſt wee not when wee pray to God (as in my writings I have preſſed it) carefully examine and conſider with our ſelves, whether that which wee pray for, be within the compaſſe of this rule, namely, whether God in his word doth commaund us to aſke ſuch a thing which wee deſire to have, and whether hee doth promiſe upon our calling to beſtow it upon us? ought wee not thus to doe, and who can deny it? Or is it ſufficient upon all occaſions to come to God onely with an <hi>If?</hi> Is that the prayer wherein hee delighteth? What doe you thinke then of this? put caſe, an honeſt, learned &amp; true hearted Miniſter, doth for the preſent want meanes, as alſo a place to exerciſe his calling, I preſume you will ſay in this caſe, pray hee muſt. Well be it ſo. Now hee frames his petition thus; Oh Lord, I beſeech thee, if it be thy will give me one of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> his places; one of them at Tedbury, or els that at Horſeleigh, whereby I may both exerciſe my calling, and alſo ger my mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. What doe you thinke of this petition? Is it agreeable to Gods will, thô hee here putteth in this word <hi>If,</hi> and ſay, If it be thy will give it me? Or doth God delight in this kind of praying? I trowe you will anſwer, No; and conclude with mee in theſe words, (thô now recorded by you as an errour) Hee doth rudely and unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nay ignorantly run to God, thô <hi>If</hi> be in. And doth not the word of God warrant this? Nay when men ſhall pray to God for this, or any other thing, as have no ground from his word (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they doe thruſt in an <hi>If</hi>) ſhall they not be ſent away emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Will not the Lord plead to ſuch petitioners, <hi>Non est factum,</hi> I made no ſuch promiſe? Will he delight in ſuch babling? Are not theſe the things which I ſpake of in my writings, and who can juſtly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7192:33"/>except againſt them? Doe not the Scriptures teach ſo much? why then doe you laſh the Scriptures (as containing dangerous poſitions) upon my backe? why have you peeced up together certain ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, ſome of mine, and ſome of your owne, and ſent them to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as dangerous aſſertions? Doe you not by this meanes labour to caſt a miſt before the Readers eyes, that ſo hee can not clearely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave my meaning? For in theſe your laſt collections, you deale very ſtrangly, in that you doe ſo tye them together with your owne chaines, as that the Reader cannot conceave, but that they doe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one the other directly in my writings, as you have here placed them: when as you put part of that, which is in the ſecond place, firſt, and this ſentence (hee delighteth not in ſuch bablings) which is laſt, you have put in the middle betweene another ſaying, leaving out the ground upon which it is ſpoken, and all other words and paſſages, which I uſe to make it plaine. This is brave dealing is it not? Doe you thinke to make good by this meanes, what you have ſpoken? which is (as tis reported) this: That I doe maintaine blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; which you labour to proove by theſe words: The Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth not in ſuch bablings. I pray you, what is that which I ſay is babling? Is it not this? namely, to pray to God for ſuch things (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>If,</hi> be thruſt in) as have no ground from the word? Is this blaſphemy? Iudge righteous judgement. And henceforth (I pray you) keepe your eyes in your head; tis the place (as Salomon ſaith Eccleſ. 2.14.) where a wiſe mans eyes are. Conſider before hand what the iſſue will be. It had bene well, if you had obſerved this rule, before you had preſumed to put in practiſe ſuch things as theſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixt place in my writings runneth thus: <hi>Let him not</hi> (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, thy heart) <hi>ſhift thee off with this, or the like poore excuſe:</hi> The Lord doth not ſee it good for thee; but rather tell him plainely thou knoweſt the Lord doth ſee it good for thee, becauſe hee hath both commaunded thee to aſke it of him, and hath alſo promiſed to give it; but thou (Oh falſe heart) with ſome or one of thoſe before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, haſt made mee unworthy of the thing which I have aſked, unſufficient to apprehend the promiſe, and to receave it.</p>
               <p>The ground of this ſpeech is this: A little before I having ſhewed that the uſe of that point, which wee affirmed, did ſerve to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of us in our wants, and that becauſe of our weakneſſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7192:34"/>wee have made our ſelves unworthy of many temporall bleſſings: I added this exhortation; Oh then, whoſoever thou art, whenſoever thou prayeſt unto God, and hee will not be found of thee, retire quickly to thy owne heart, and ſay unto him (as tis there more fully expreſſed) thou haſt cauſed my loving Father to frowne upon mee, and cover himſelf in a cloud, ſo that my prayers cannot paſſe through, either in wanting or fayling in ſome or one of thoſe particulars, required in prayer. Whereupon I inferred this ſaying; Let him not (namely thy heart) ſhift thee off with this or the like poore excuſe, &amp;c. as tis before repeated. Now wherein I pray you, is there any errour or juſt cauſe to except againſt mee, for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a Saint of God may ſay, that hee doth know the Lord doth ſee thoſe things good for him, for the which hee hath both eommaunded him to aſke, and promiſed to give him? Are not thoſe things good for Gods people, which God doth commaund them to aſke, and promiſe to give them? How is it that you except againſt it? Can you find any of Gods ſervants thus reaſoning in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, concerning any particular thing which God hath promiſed them? and doth the Lord indeed know whether this or that, which hee hath promiſed mee, be good for me? Did Abraham make any ſuch queſtion concerning thoſe promiſes Gen. 17. namely, whether it was good for him to be a father of many nations, and that his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhould poſſeſſe Canaan? Or did Moſes and the Iſraelits make any ſuch queſtion? Nay is there any place in the Scripture, which doth teach us that wee are to doubt, whether thoſe things, which God hath commaunded us to aſke, and promiſed to give, are good for us? Nay contraryly did not the Saints rather urge God for and with his promiſe? Note that example (omitting many others) of Ichoſaphat 2. Cron. 20, when hee was compaſſed about by his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hee proclaimed a faſt, and did remember God of that promiſe (as appeareth verſ. 9.) which was made long before 1. King. 8.37. Hee made no queſtion, but that it was good for them to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſeeing (they performing what God required) hee had promiſed the ſame. What hereſy is in this thinke you? But now (Oh lamentable to conſider) that men ſhould (at the leaſt) thinke, there is little els but hereſy and blaſphemy in my writings; you deale with them as unkindly, as Hanun (2. Sam. 10.14.) dealt with Davids ſervants; you have ſhaved off the one halfe, and cut off many of my words in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7192:34"/>middle, to the deſtroying of their meaning, and deceaving of the reader. For you have here left out all the expoſitory words, ſo that the Reader cannot gather any other but that I affirme, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wee deſire of God, wee are ſure it is good for us, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is neither commanded to be aſked nor promiſed to be given. And this is that which is generally rumoured about the Country. In this you deale very corruptly. The Lord open your eyes, that you may ſee your folly, and graunt that I may never labour to grace my owne proceedings by any unjuſt ſcandalizing, and diſgracing others.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſeventh place (yet in it you have left out ſome of my words) is repeated not much amiſſe, and it will be eaſily cleared from being either erronious or dangerous. All the errour or daunger (as I conceive) you ſuppoſe to be in this place, is in that I bid the conditionall <hi>(If)</hi> to come out from among the petitions of the Lords prayer, and content himſelf with ſome meaner place, ſeeing hee was never placed there by Chriſts appointment. This if any (as I thinke) you ſuppoſe to be dangerous. Now that this ſpeech doth containe neither matter of daunger or errour, it ſhall plainly appeare to all. That prayer which wee call the Lords prayer, and ſo call it (as in my writings is ſpecified) becauſe it is the Lord Chriſts owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, is declared by the Euangeliſt Mathew to us (you dare not deny it) as hee received it from Chriſt. Now our Saviour Chriſt in all that forme of prayer (and indeed it is <hi>exemplar abſolutiſſimum</hi> ſuch an abſolute one, as that there is nothing eſſentiall to prayer wanting, (as wee have declared) neither is there any thing ſuperfluous) doth not uſe this conditionall <hi>If,</hi> and therefore there is no danger or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in ſaying, that the conditionall <hi>If</hi> was never placed in the Lords prayer by Chriſts appointment. For had <hi>If</hi> bene eſſentiall to prayer, Chriſt could not have left it out of his forme of prayer, unleſſe hee had left us an imperfect forme, as wanting either will or ſkill to make ſuch a forme, which could not be mended. And who dare to affirme Chriſts forme to be imperfect, or once goe about to adde one particle to the further perfecting of it? And therefore why may wee not without blame (<hi>If</hi> being thruſt in by man at any time, and not placed there by Chriſt) bid him come out from among the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of the Lords prayer? And why may we not boldly ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controlment, as our Saviour, to the plant not planted by his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7192:35"/>Father, thou ſhalt be rooted out; for doth hee not robbe God of his glory, in that he doth goe about to make man thinke, that Chriſts forme of prayer, without him, is not ſo current? And doth hee not deprive us of many bleſſings now, as well as hee kept the Father in Mark. 9.22. without the bleſſing, for indeed, how ſhall a man that doubteth thinke (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iames ſaith chap. 1.7.) to receive any thing of the Lord? And hath hee not luld us aſleepe in ſecurity, when as by his meaning wee have bene perſwaded to thinke, all is well, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding many things have bene amiſſe in us, which hath cauſed God to ſtop his eares at our cryes, and hid himſelf in a cloude, ſo that our prayers could not paſſe through? Speake now, and ſpeake truely, what errour is there in this ſaying?</p>
               <p n="8">8. The eight place in my writing runneth thus: So then to affirme the promiſes of God for temporall things, are conditionall (according to your owne words) is a doctrine of mans invention, and not of God; and certainly to make the beſt of it, it is but as one of the Popes unwritten verities. This ſpeech (you know) is in my anſwer to your firſt argument, wherein I affirme no more, but what I have ground, both from the Scriptures, as alſo from your owne words, as in my ſayd anſwer is plainely prooved. Your argument runneth thus: Thoſe promiſes which have conditions implyed in them, cannot abſolutely be relyed upon, or expected, for our faith is grounded upon the promiſes; but the promiſe for outward things (although but neceſſary) are ſo. Ergo. In this argument I denyed your Minor propoſition, being altogether untrue, and contrary to ſound doctrine. This I made plainely appeare in that (as is there ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified) the will of God (ſo much of his will as is neceſſary for man to knowe) is revealed in the Scriptures, which Scriptures, Gods writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities, are abſolutely ſufficient to inſtruct us in all ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which I prooved by that of the Apoſtle 2. Tim. 3.15. Now (ſayd I) whereas you affirme, that the promiſes for temporals are conditionall, notwithſtanding in the whole Scriptures there is no condition expreſſed, what is it els but to affirme, that God hath not revealed ſo much of his will in the Scriptures, as is needfull for us to knowe. And to make this appeare, I brought your owne words to be your judge, as it doth there thus follow: You ſay that this poſition of yours (namely, that the promiſes for temporall things are condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall) is one of Gods truthes (for you preſſe it upon men to beleeve
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7192:35"/>as a truth from God) and yet you ſay, that God hath not expreſſed this truth in his word; for you ſay, it is implyed, &amp;c. From which premiſes I drew this concluſion: So then to affirme the promiſes of God for temporall things, are conditionall, is a doctrine of mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and not of God; and certainly to make the beſt of it, it is but as one of the Popes unwritten verities. And thus much is made plaine by your owne words, as they immediatly follow. Unwritten you confeſſe it is, for if any man ſhould but aſke you, where in the Scriptures doth God ſay the promiſes are conditionall? you have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to anſwer (for ought I know) but this, the condition is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, &amp;c. Now whether or not I have in this ſpeech affirmed any more, but what the Scriptures, as alſo your owne words doe cleare, let the unpartiall and honeſt hearted judge.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The ninth place runneth thus in my writing: For you know and muſt needs confeſſe, that the Lord Levit. 26. and Deuter. 28. made abſolutely to his people Iſrael precious promiſes. In which promiſes there is no condition implyed, &amp;c. Now by this and that which followeth, I made it plaine, even to the weakeſt capacity, that that of Lament the fowerth, which you alleaged to proove the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be conditionall, is not any thing at all to the purpoſe. For your Minor propoſition being denyed, you labour to proove it by that place thus: The Lord for the ſinnes of his people doth ſtrippe them of outward comforts, ſome times in part, ſome times wholy unto death; (as you prooved Lament. 4.15.) Ergo the promiſes of outward things have conditions implyed in them, and are not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely intended. This was your doctrine. And how doth this proove the promiſes to be conditionall? Eſpecially ſeeing the Lord (as in my anſwer is manifeſted) upon condition of their obedience, did abſolutely promiſe to give them ſuch and ſuch bleſſings. If (ſaith he) thou obey, (.i.) thou obeying his commaundements, all theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall come upon thee; But if thou diſobey, (.i.) thou diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my commandements, all theſe curſes ſhall come upon thee, &amp;c. Now while Iſrael walked with God in ſincerity, they wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that which God promiſed them, as the current of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe proove: But they rebelling againſt him (for they pluckt away the ſhoulder Zach. 7.11.) He brought upon them this plague of famine, which the Prophet Ieremy doth here bewaile. The pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full women Lament. 4.10. (according as hee had threatned Lev. 26.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7192:36"/>and Deuteron. 28.) did eat their owne children for want of other meat. What now (as I there demaunded the queſtion) was the cauſe of this plague of famine? Your owne words there is the anſwer. The Lord did viſite them thus for their ſinnes. So then by this it doth appeare, that in prooving your argument, you have ſpoken againſt your ſelf, in that you affirme the ſinne and rebellion of the Iewes was the cauſe why God did thus plague them. And is not this the thing which I labour to defend (yet now by you oppoſed) namely, that it is our (as it was their) ignorance, rebellion &amp; infidelity which doth robbe us of many bleſſings, and bring upon us many puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. So that for ought I ſee you are contrary to your ſelf: Let all men now judge what daunger there is in that which I have written: Notwithſtanding you labour to make men thinke as bad of it, as poſſibly you can, in that you here in this place leave out thoſe Scriptures, which I uſe to make that plaine, which I have ſayd, as if there was no warrant for what I ſpeake: The Lord lay not this your injurious dealing to your charge.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The tenth place in my writing is thus: The Saints of God may and ought, as abſolutely depend upon the promiſes of God, for their dayly bread, (i.) for things neceſſary, as they may for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their ſinnes. This point is confirmed thus: It is indifferently acknowledged by our whole Church, that the promiſes of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the pardon of ſinnes, and life eternall, ought abſolutely to be depended upon, without any ſcruple, &amp;c. The ground of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon God for ſoule or body, is his promiſes, which God in Chriſt made to all his ſervants, as the Apoſtle prooveth 2. Corinth. 11.14. all the promiſes (as well temporaries as ſpiritualls) are in Chriſt Yea, and in him Amen. Now that God in his word hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his ſervants things neceſſary for the body as well as for the ſoule, I made it appeare in divers places. As that of Peter 2. Epiſt. 1.3. Math. 6.25. to the end. Rom. 8.32. and Iohn 15.7. with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Scriptures and reaſons, which are too long here to repeat, all which you have left out, as if I had no ground for what I ſpeake. And here (I feare your ſtudy was to entangle) you have put downe this poſition, conſiſting partly of your owne words, and partly of mine, without quoting that Scripture, which I had uſed to proove it. As alſo you have thruſt in this parentheſis of your owne (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Pſal. 73.) why could you not (if you had meant plainely)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7192:36"/>have quoted ſome or one of thoſe Scriptures, which I cited to proove this poſition, as well as you have cited this in a parentheſis, which is none of mine, that ſo the Reader might have compared yours &amp; mine together? But I perceive your meaning.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The eleventh place runneth thus in my writing: Hence it was (as I conceive, ſeeing to be perſecuted for the truth, is ſuch a bleſſed thing) that thoſe tortured Saints, Heb. 11.35. accepted not delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they might obtaine a better reſurrection; and this made S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul Act. 21.13. willing and ready not to be bound onely, but alſo to dye at Ieruſalem for the name of the Lord Ieſus. In my anſwer to your firſt argument it is thus written: Thoſe in Heb. 11.37. ſuffered thoſe things for the truthes ſake; neither did they accept deliverance. And Paul alſo 2. Cor. 11.37. ſuffered thoſe things for the Goſpels ſake in caſe of perſecution, as hee teſtifieth 2. Tim. 1.12. which kind of ſufferings, both of Paul and thoſe in the Hebrewes, are bleſſings, and the portions of Gods ſervants, not to be prayed againſt, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoyced in, &amp;c. There it is thus written briefly, becauſe in the other place I did more fully explane, and expreſſe my ſelf, unto which I referred you, that ſo you might underſtand what I meant in theſe ſhort ſpeeches, as in my ſaid anſwer you might have ſeene. Now wherein doth this, which I have written, diſagree from the word of God? Yet (as it ſeemes) you taxe theſe for dangerous poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; namely to ſay, firſt that to be perſecuted for the truth, is a bleſſed thing. And ſecondly that thoſe tortured Saints Heb. 11. (ſeeing to be perſecuted for the truth, is ſuch a bleſſed thing) accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not deliverance, that they might obtaine a better reſurrection. And thirdly that wee have no warrant to pray at all againſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that wee ſhall not ſuffer. Now the word of God warranting the truth of all theſe poſitions, then there is no danger in them; but the word of God doth warrant them to be true as it is, and will be further prooved.</p>
               <p>Firſt that to <hi>be perſecuted for the truth, and for righteouſneſse ſake, is a bleſsed thing,</hi> thoſe Scriptures Math. 5.10.11. &amp; 1. Pet. 3. and 4. chap. and the 14. verſ. quoted in my writings, doe plainely proove, &amp; tis further manifeſted in divers other places. So that what I affirme concerning perſecution, is no more but what the word of God doth avouch to be true.</p>
               <p>I ſay that perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake is a bleſſing, or to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7192:37"/>be perſecuted for the truth, is a bleſſed thing, and thus much is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Heb. 11.26. where it is ſaid, that <hi>Moſes esteemed the reproach of Christ greater riches, then the treaſures of Egypt.</hi> Moſes wee ſee (and tis recorded by the holy Ghoſt for a fruit of faith) counted the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach for Chriſt, or perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake, a bleſſing, a favour, or rich treaſure of great waight, <hi>Quae vel omnia Regum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronorum diademata facilè exupera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And did not the Apoſtles alſo thus eſteeme it, when as they <hi>rejoyced</hi> Act. 5.41. <hi>that they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name?</hi> And did not Paul <hi>glory in the croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 6.14? Did Moſes account the croſſe of Chriſt ſuch a rich favour, and did the Apoſtles rejoyce that they were counted worrhy to have a part in it? And may not I affirme, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hereſy, that perſecution for the name of Chriſt, is a bleſſing, or a bleſſed thing? Eſpecially ſeeing in the firſt place (as wee may further add) Gods name is thereby glorified, as I before prooved from that of Peter 1. Epiſt. 4.14. And ſecondly in that thereby the Goſpell is furthered, and its faithfull profeſſors <hi>imboldened to ſpeake the word without feare,</hi> as tis to be ſeene Philip. 1.12.13.14. And thirdly ſeeing the reward of thoſe that doe ſuffer for Chriſt, is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, for <hi>theirs is the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> And to ſpeake truely, this is a favour which God giveth to his Saints for a ſigne: the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and that in that they are perſecuted for righteouſneſſe, are ſaid to be bleſſed, and thereby they are ſure, the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is theirs. So that (as one neately obſerveth) <hi>all our fiery tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions fall under the nature and definition of Sacraments, they are ſo many viſible ſignes of inviſible graces,</hi> without this Sacrament, this fire of tribulation a man cannot be ſo ſure of his ſalvation, <hi>for all that will live godly, ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> 2. Tim. 3.12. which is <hi>indeed an evident token of a mans ſalvation, and that of God: being given to him in the behalfe of Christ,</hi> (Philip. 1, 28.29.) <hi>not onely to beleeve in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> By this I hope you ſee that to ſay perſecution, is a bleſſing, or to be perſecuted for the truth, is a bleſſed thing, is cleared from being dangerous. And I doubt not, but ſo will the ſecond alſo: for in ſaying that thoſe tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Saints accepted not deliverance, that they might obtaine a better reſurrection, I ſay no more, but what the holy Ghoſt expreſly ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. And whereas I affirme the conſideration of the bleſſedneſſe of perſecution, was a motive which did ſtirre up to hold faſt the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7192:37"/>profeſſion of their faith, and to be willing and ready to reſiſt even to blood, it is no more but what the Apoſtle here teacheth. Hee tells us verſ. 26. that Moſes eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt greater riches, then the treaſures of Egypt; for hee had reſpect to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward. <hi>Non temerè mens in judicando reſolvit in alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram partem</hi> (as one ſaith upon the place) <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in deliberando intue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur in praemij largitionem.</hi> Was not the recompence of the reward now a motive which mooved Moſes to make this choiſe, and to eſteeme the reproach of Chriſt as he did? And had not theſe tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Saints, not accepting deliverance, a reſpect to the recompence of the reward too, thinke you? Was not the joye that was ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, a motive to perſwade them patiently to indure the croſſe, and to deſpiſe the ſhame? Yea doe not the very words there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing proove ſo much? If this be true (and who can deny it?) wherein am I to be blamed, for ſaying that, <hi>Hence it was (ſeeing to be perſecuted for the truth, is ſuch a bleſſed thing) that the tortured Saints accepted not deliverance, that they might obtaine a better reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in the third place, <hi>That wee have no warrant to pray at all against perſecutions, that wee ſhall not ſuffer;</hi> the Scriptures doe plainely ſhew, as thoſe Scriptures, which I have quoted in my writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, concerning this thing, doe plainely manifeſt. <hi>It is</hi> (as I have already ſaid) <hi>the portion of Gods people to ſuffer perſecutions,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out drinking this potion of tribulations here, there is no drinking of the full cup of pleaſures in heaven. Wee muſt be with Chriſt in the garden, and pertake of his afflictions, or els wee ſhall not be with him in Paradice, and pertake of his pleaſures. <hi>If wee ſuffer with Christ</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle 2. Tim. 2.12.) <hi>wee ſhall alſo raigne with him.</hi> If wee are with Chriſt in his afflictions, wee ſhall be with him alſo in his eluctation, in his Triumph, els not.</p>
               <p>Conſider this (I pray you) and then tell me whether wee have any warrant from the word to pray at all againſt perſecutions, the afflictions of the Goſpell that wee ſhall not ſuffer; ſeeing without ſuffering with Chriſt, there is no raigning with him. Paul (I finde) exhorted Timothy (2. Epiſt. 1.8.) to the partaking of the afflictions of the Goſpell, but I find not any warrant, any place, wherein God doth commaund us to pray againſt perſecution, or promiſe us that wee ſhall not ſuffer. If you or any one ſhall now aſke, how wee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7192:38"/>muſt pray in time of perſecution? The anſwer is thus already made in my ſaid writings: <hi>All the prayers that wee are to make in this caſe, muſt be to deſire the Lord, that he would give us ſtrength and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience manfully to perſevere in the truth, and that he would make us instruments of his glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus what I affirme in my writings, concerning perſecution, and thoſe tortured Saints Heb. 11. is cleared by the Scriptures from being dangerous.</p>
               <p>But now to your collection: In which writing (as before is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified) I uſe the very phraſe of the Scripture, which you have left out, and here you bring me in to affirme, that the Martyrs Heb. 11. that are ſaid not to accept <hi>deliverance, did refuſe it,</hi> or they might have bene deluded if they would, which words are not in all my writings, but they are of your owne invention: So that the Reader cannot conceive, but that I affirme, thoſe Martyrs had deliverance offered them, but they refuſed to injoy their liberty together with the freedome of their conſciences. And to the end you might ſtrengthen theſe conceits, you have added this parentheſis of your owne (ſo the Martyrs perſecuted themſelves.) In which ſaying you doe but labour to foreſtall the judgement of the Reader, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe him with a bad conceit of what I have written before, indeed hee doth truely underſtand, or know what I have written, that ſo you might the eaſier ſhape all to your owne foote. Beſids in this your extraction, you have not placed thoſe words which are mine, as I have written them; but you have taken ſome from the anſwer to your firſt argument, and ſome from your other writing: whereas you had done better, had you placed my words, and mine onely in their proper places. I leave it to your conſcience what you inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in doing the contrary. Meane time (I am ſure) I undergo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcandalls and foule reproaches, which by reaſon of you, and your proceedings are moſt falſely laid upon me.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The twalefth place runneth thus in my writing: <hi>Concerning thoſe 2 places which you produce to proove your poſition, you doe greatly miſtake the true meaning of the holy Ghost in them: For the meaning of the holy Ghost in that of Eccleſ. 9.1.2.3. is quite contrary to your interpretation. For your interpretation is according to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world, which judgement the holy Ghoſt doth condemne, as appeareth verſ. 3. for ſaith hee, this is an evill among all things that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7192:38"/>are done under the Sunne, &amp;c. Men of the world judge it ſo but what then? becauſe they ſay there is no difference betweene the juſt and the unjuſt, concerning theſe things, muſt their ſaying therefore be true? Alas it is no ſuch matter, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This (you know) is written in my anſwer to your third argument, wherein I give you to underſtand, that you have greatly miſtaken the true meaning of thoſe 2 places, which you alleadged to proove your poſition; and that the meaning of the holy Ghoſt in that of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 9.1.2. is contrary to your interpretation. Now what is your interpretation of thoſe words? Is it not this? namely, <hi>that there is no certaine bettering of the outward ſtate by faith and grace?</hi> For after you had repeated the words of Eccleſ. 9.1.2. you ſay thus: <hi>Which could not be ſo, if there were any certaine bettering of the outward estate by faith and grace.</hi> So that here you make the Wiſeman to patronize your ſaying, and that theſe words of yours <hi>(There is no certaine bettering of the outward estate by faith and grace) is the ſumme or meaning of the holy Ghost in them.</hi> Whereby it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that you make the meaning of the holy Ghoſt to be according to the judgement of the world. For you make the holy Ghoſt to patronize this ſpeech, <hi>There is no certaine bettering of the outward eſtate by faith and grace,</hi> which ſaying is the ſaying or judgement of the world, and condemned by the holy Ghoſt verſ. 3. Now that the holy Ghoſt doth condemne your judgement, being (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) but the judgement of the world, appeareth plainely, in that is ſhewed in this verſe, that you offer violence to that text, in drawing a concluſion, which hath no ſound footing from it, the meaning of it being (as appeareth by this verſe) contrary to your interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But here (notwithſtanding that before ſpecified) you give out in this collection that I affirme; that when Salomon ſaith Eccleſ. 9.2. all things come alike to all, and there is one event, &amp;c. hee ſpeaketh not as the truth is, but according to the judgement and cenſure of the world, &amp;c. Is there any ſuch ſaying in my writings? or doe I ſay that Salomon in that place ſpeaketh not as the truth is? I remember indeed, that I have ſaid (and ſo doe ſtill) that your interpretation of that place, is not as the truth is, but according to the judgement of the world; but you find not this in all my writings, that Salomon in this place ſpeaketh not as the truth is. What is this better then a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7192:39"/>plaine falſifying of my writings, and a laying falſe imputations upon me? But let this paſſe; and in concluſion I pray you take notiſe, that an argument framed according to the true intent and meaning of the holy Ghoſt in that of Eccleſ. 9.1.2. will not in any meaſure contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict what I have affirmed, concerning prayer for outward bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The thyrteenth place is thus in my writings: <hi>In this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I deny your Major propoſition, a doctrine more fit to be ſpued out, then taught in the Church of Chriſt, being as was your firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, a chief pillar of the Church of Rome. This wee will make plainely to appeare: Whatſoever is mans duety to obſerve in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that muſt be commanded by God, for nothing but a commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God can make a man owe a duety to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ground of that concluſion, which is there prooved by that of Eccleſ. 12.13. and that of our Saviour Math. 28.20. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I inferred this ſpeech: <hi>Now if any man ſhall teach men to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any thing as a duety, which God hath not commaunded, tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his commiſſion: A created worſhip, a worſhip of his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, which God never required.</hi> What is the whole drift of my ſpeech, or what is the doctrine which I ſaid was more fit to be ſpued out, then taught in the Church of Chriſt? Was it not this? Namely, to make examples, without any commandement, to be the ground of a duety, ſeeing ſuch ſervice (as in my writings is prooved) is will-worſhip, and will-worſhip is idolatrie. And wherein (if you ſpeake truely) can you find fault with any thing, which I have there writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? For is will-worſhip, which is idolatry, fit to be taught, or caſt out of the Church of Chriſt? and is not that will-worſhip, or a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſervice, which is offered to God, without the authority of any commaundement? For who requires ſuch a ſervice at thy hands? Nay if this doctrine was but reaſonably preſſed; Examples without the authority of any commandement, are ſufficient grounds of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes; or examples (thô commanded) are equivalent with precepts in Gods worſhip, would it not looke more towards Rome then Sion? There is great difference betweene following the examples of the Saints in things indifferent, as things indifferent, &amp; betweene making their examples without any commandement, to be the ground of a duety. In the firſt wee ſhew our Chriſtian liberty, it is not forbidden: In the other wee ſhew voluntary humility, in creating ſuch a ſervice, which never came into Gods heart to require of us. Had you well
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7192:39"/>conſidered the drift of my writings in this particular (all by-ends layd aſide) you could not (me think) have dealt with it ſo injuriouſly as you have; but it ſeemes you are glad to catch any advatage, where indeed there is none. For here you have in that confuſed manner patcht to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether this collection, partly with my words, and partly with your owne, as that the reader cannot rightly conceive the drift or ground of my writings, concerning this particular. I would you had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Readers view my writings, and mine onely in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per kinde, then had you bene free from blame, and I from many ſcandalls.</p>
               <p n="14">14. For anſwer to this fourthteenth place, I referre you to that which I have already written, from whence you gathered this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and there I doubt not you will ſee a plaine difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Praying and Saying.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Concerning the fiftenth place. I referre you and the Reader to that which I have already written in my anſwer to your fifth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, from whence you drew this collection. The ſumme where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is to ſhew that this ground of yours, is very weake to contradict a commandement, and nullify a promiſe, ſeeing it is uncertain why there Paul prayed for Trophymus his health, and could not recover him; for who knoweth whether Trophymus did dye, or recover of that ſickneſſe? for my part (as I ſaid before) <hi>I know not how this can be rightly reſolved, unleſse you can call either Paul or Trophymus from the dead againe.</hi> And what can you make of this? You labour indeed to make it ſeeme as bad as may be, for why els have you not ſet downe the ſame words, which are written in your Argument, and repeatingly uſed by me in my anſwer?</p>
               <p n="16">16. In this ſixtenth place you deale very injuriouſly, in that you have ſet it downe for one of my Aſſertions, notwithſtanding there is no ground for it in all my writings. I remember indeed that in a letter I wrote this unto you: Whereas you ſay (where I repeated your owne words) that abſolute prayer for temporall neceſſaries (the tenent which wee hold) is an uncouth and proud conceit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrant, tending to evill, you doe in that ſaying no leſſe then blaſpheme the truth. And in the concluſion of my anſwer to your arguments, I add this ſpeech: <hi>It is</hi> (namely your opinion) <hi>a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the promiſes, beſids their intendement, and the teaching of an ignorant and unwarrantable kind of praying.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:7192:40"/>
               <p> In theſe ſayings I affirme, firſt that you doe no better then blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the truth, in that you ſay this opinion, namely, <hi>That tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neceſsary bleſſings ought to be prayed for, without doubting and wavering, &amp;c.</hi> (being the ground of our tenent) <hi>is an uncouth and proud conceit, without warrant tending to evill. And ſecondly, that your opinion contained in your Arguments, is a perverting of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes beſids their intendement, and the teaching of an ignorant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable kind of praying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if it doth appeare that theſe above named grounds, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning praying for outward neceſſaries, are warranted for truth by the Word of God, then you muſt confeſſe your raſhneſſe in cenſuring; for no one can ſay, that any part of Gods truth is a proud conceit, tending to evill, and not blaſpheme it. And furthermore if it appeare that the drift of your Arguments is to alter the nature of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, contradict commandements, and to eſtabliſh a will-worſhip, then it is an ignorant and unwarrantable kind of praying; for igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is the mother of will-worſhip, and to teach will-worſhip, is to teach but an ignorant kind of ſervice.</p>
               <p>Now whether the grounds of my writings (which you ſay is a proud conceit) are agreeable to the truth or not; or whether your arguments doe bend their forces to alter the nature of the promiſes, contradict commaundements, and ſo eſtabliſh any thing more but a will-worſhip, a duety, which God never commanded, let our writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings witneſſe.</p>
               <p>But you here give out without any <hi>If,</hi> yet abſolutely falſe, that I affirme, <hi>That for any to teach men to pray with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed, is to blaspheme the truth, &amp;c.</hi> whereby you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, which you abſolutely affirme, That the ground and drift of my writings is to proove, that no man, without blaſpheming the truth, and teaching of an ignorant and unfaithfull kind of praying, can teach men to pray with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed. And to the end you might faſten this falſe imputation on me, and my writings, you have ſo framed this extraction, as that it doth agree with the title or preface of theſe your learned collections, which you ſay is the ground of my writings. There you profeſſe that the matter wee ſtand for, is praying for temporall bleſſings in the particulars, without any condition, expreſſed or implyed of the will of God therein; and here (to make both ends meete) you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7192:40"/>bring me in to conclude; That for any to teach men to pray with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed, is to blaſpheme the truth, &amp;c. As if this was the principall thing I aymed at; to proove in that which I have written, namely, that we muſt not pray for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed in his word.</p>
               <p>Alas <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice,</hi> is this the thing which I hold, concerning praying for outward bleſſings? or is there any ſuch thing written in thoſe papers, which I ſent unto you? Who that had his 5 wits about him, would once avouch it? Eſpecially ſeeing the principall thing I aymed at, and preſſed in them, was to perſwade men to frame all their prayers according to Gods will, revealed or expreſſed in his word. And can any petitions be made with more humble ſubmiſſion to the will of God, then when they are made agreeable to his word, wherein his will is revealed? This is the will of him that ſent me (ſaith Chriſt) that ye keepe my commaundements. And againe, this is the will of God, that ye beleeve in Ieſus Chriſt, whom hee hath ſent. And doe wee not pray with ſubmiſſion to the will of God, when our prayers are made agreeable to his word? Nay how can a man pray to God for this or that, which hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to aſke, and beleeve to receive that which hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give, and yet ſuch petitions not made with ſubmiſſion, and aggreeable to his will. Unlooſe this knot that can, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> having firſt laid his foundation (namely the Title) pretending it (thô falſely) to be mine: And ſecondly the particular Aſſertions of his calling from my ſayd writings, affirming that his ſayd collections (but how true it is, curteous Reader, thou mayſt plainely ſee) doe agree with my writings; whereunto (with more boldneſſe then wellcome) hee ſubſcribed my name. Hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, and in the third place layes downe a certaine diſtinction of faith of his collecting, from whence hee drew certain concluſions. And here thus it followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:7192:41"/>
               <head>THIRD PART. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Boye <hi>his distinction of faith, wherein the foundation of his building is diſcovered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEe diſtinguiſh faith into 2 ſorts; the one is called juſtifying or eternall faith, becauſe the object of it is eternall, to wit, the eternall promiſes.</p>
               <p>The other is called temporary, becauſe the object of it is temporall, concerning temporall things, both which are required in Gods ſervants: the one to keepe the ſoule to eternall life; the other to preſerve the corporall life here, for the juſt ſhall live by faith. <hi>Totidem verbis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which it followes;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all his quotations of Scripture, concerning faith in the promiſes, are to no purpoſe, ſeeing they intend the juſtifying faith onely; as that the juſt ſhall live by faith, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That wee have no promiſes at all concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, for that there are no promiſes made to a temporary faith, nor to temporaryes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That none can have helpe in their greateſt miſery; for a temporary faith doth them fayle, Math. 13.21.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That a juſtifying faith is not ſufficient for matters of this life, and temporalls, but there is need of another kind to be joyned with it, for (ſo hee ſaith) both theſe kinds are the gifts of God.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Sic debile fundamentum fallit opus.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <closer>
                  <signed>EDW. NORRICE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Anſwer to this third Part.</head>
               <p>FOr any one to ſpeake and affirme any untruth, thô the matter it ſelf be of no great conſequence, is neither laudable or approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with God, or honeſt men. Notwithſtanding you have not onely
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7192:41"/>here affirmed an untruth, which is of no great conſequence, but alſo in a matter (at leaſt as the Reader may convert it) of ſome waight. For here you ſay that you have tranſcribed this diſtinction <hi>(totidem verbis)</hi> just in ſo many words, as I have written it: when as you have converted ſome of my words into your owne, and in ſtead of this ſaying in my writings <hi>(the other to preſerve and provide neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for the body, while God ſhall give him life, &amp;c.)</hi> You have put downe theſe words (the other to preſerve the corporall life here, &amp;c.) In the altering of which ſentence, I know not your intentions; but this I am ſure of, it doth proove that to be untrue which you here affirme, namely, that my diſtinction of faith is here written, <hi>totidem verbis.</hi> I hope your pen doth not run ſo in other matters, as it hath done in this; where it tranſcribes not truely ſix lines without ſending with it an untruth? But let this paſſe. I proceede to the diſtinction it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Though our Apoſtle ſaith Epheſ. 4.5. there is one faith, that is, one faith that juſtifyeth unto eternall ſalvation, yet hee doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that there be no more ſorts in any ſence. For beſids that one faith, which for diſtinctions ſake, wee call ſaving faith, which appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends Chriſt unto eternall life, there are (as the Scriptures doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Iames 2.19. 1. Cor. 13.2.) other ſorts of faith in another ſence.</p>
               <p>Concerning the ſorts of faith I reſted there, in this diſtinction of eternall and temporary faith, as fitteſt to the purpoſe where I uſed it. Which diſtinction (ſeeing here you moſt unworthyly except againſt it) I aggreſſe to cleare.</p>
               <p>To cleare this diſtinction then from being erronious or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, I need ſay no more, but what I have ſaid already; but to give the well-diſpoſed Reader further ſatisfaction, it will not be unmeete to have it further amplified. A little before I uſed this diſtinction, I deſired you to note (as in my writings doth appeare) that when I imputed the lacke of outward neceſſaries, to the lacke of faith, I did not call the faith of Gods ſervants into queſtion, whereby they are juſtified before God, ſeeing a man (as I acknowledged) may have faith to juſtify himſelf before God, and yet want faith in apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a temporall promiſe. Whereupon I inferred this diſtinction of <hi>faith Eternall and Temporary:</hi> Not calling it temporary for that it ſelf indureth for a time, but ſo calling it (as the words are) for the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7192:42"/>
                  <hi>object it apprehendeth, which is ſome temporary promiſe, or bleſſing,</hi> and the other <hi>Eternall, for the eternall promiſe it apprehendeth.</hi> Which 2. ſorts of faith (as the words immediately follow) being divers in reſpect of their ſeverall object, each of them ought to be referred to his proper object. Eternall or juſtifying faith to eternall promiſes; and Temporary faith to temporall promiſes. So then as you ſay (and that truely) whoſoever commeth ſhort of Heaven, it is becauſe hee wanteth faith in apprehending the eternall promiſes: So wee ſay (and that truely) that whoſoever wanteth bread, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee lacketh faith in apprehending the temporall promiſes. So farre there. To this purpoſe I alſo ſpake in my anſwer to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of your Arguments. By which words it is plaine, in what reſpect I approove of this diſtinction, and call <hi>faith</hi> there <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> not in that it laſteth but for a time (as you falſely dreame) but for the object it apprehendeth, which is ſome <hi>Temporary promiſe and bleſſing;</hi> and the other I called Eternall, in that it apprehendeth eternall promiſes, or bleſſings. So then faith is diſtinguiſhed into faith eternall and tempory, in reſpect it apprehendeth ſeverall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: Which 2. apprehenſions if wee underſtand faith in that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſence, as it is defined Heb. 11.1. which is as well the evidence of things eternall, as temporall, or as it apprehendeth both eternall and temporall favours and promiſes. If I ſay wee underſtand faith in ſo generall a ſence, theſe 2. apprehenſions are but ſeverall acts of one and the ſame faith, els not.</p>
               <p>By all which briefly it doth appeare, that your excepting againſt this diſtinction, is but frivolous; and that the foundation of my building is diſcovered to be ſo firme, as that all your Petrinell flaſhes can not ſhake it, and that by your concluſions, or ſequells, you doe but labour (as it will appeare) to bring a darkneſſe upon <hi>Goſhen,</hi> which will not be, for I call faith temporary, not becauſe it laſteth for a time, but becauſe it apprehendeth temporall promiſes and bleſſings, by which it doth appeare, that your concluſions for the moſt part doe not follow from any thing which I have written, ſeeing you make tempory faith in that reſpect and ſence, as it is ſaid to laſt, but for a time to be the ground of your concluſions. And therefore to each of theſe concluſions, I returne-in this brief anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt my quotations of Scripture, concerning faith in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7192:42"/>(contrary to your ſaying) are to good purpoſe, and pertinent to the matter, ſeeing they intend that faith, which the Saints of God ought to have, to apprehend temporall promiſes and bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly that wee have as good and firme promiſes for the things of this life, as for that which is to come, notwithſtanding there are no promiſes made, either to a temporary faith in that reſpect, as you call it Temporary, namely, as it is ſaid to laſt but a while; nor to Temporaryes, that is, (as I conceive your meaning) to thoſe who are out of Chriſt Ieſus. Thus much I knew before, as alſo maintained againſt you, as appeareth in my anſwer to your third Argument. For among other your aſſertions, this is one, namely, <hi>that the very ſame dispenſation in outward things, belongs to one as to another</hi> (to the evill and the good) <hi>and there is no difference;</hi> which aſſertion I there oppoſed, and made it appeare to be a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrary to ſound doctrine; and thus much you doe now in this place acknowledge, in that you ſay, <hi>There are no promiſes made to Temporaries,</hi> that is, to wicked and ungodly perſons. So that you have juſtly brought that upon your ſelf, which you unjuſtly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt another. For (by your owne confeſſion) you contradict your ſelf: If that in your argument be true, then this here muſt needs be falſe; if this be true, that cannot be currant. I pray you take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of this, and the Lord give you an humble heart, and willing minde to confeſſe your fayling.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To your third concluſion I thus anſwer: That notwithſtanding temporary faith (ſo called by you, becauſe it laſteth but a time) doth faile, when tribulation commeth, Mat. 13.21. Yet it doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow from this diſtinction, that more can have aſſurance of helpe in their greateſt miſery, ſeeing in my diſtinction (yet not mine onely) I termed that faith tempory, not (as you faine would have me) becauſe it laſteth for a time, but becauſe it apprehendeth tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall promiſes, and bleſſings. Nay doe not I labour to perſwade the Saints of God to beleeve that they may have aſſurance of helpe, and deliverance in and out of temporall <hi>plagues</hi> and miſcryes, if they are not found to lacke <hi>temporary faith,</hi> that is a firme and ſtedfaſt apprehenſion of the temporall promiſes, which God in Chriſt Ieſus (as the eternall promiſes) have firmely made to all his ſervants?</p>
               <p n="4">4. To the fourth concluſion I anſwer, That if by faith here you underſtand faith in ſo generall a ſence, as it is in that of Heb. 11.1.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7192:43"/>that is, as it apprehendeth both temporail and eternall promiſes, it is ſufficient, both for the matters of this life, and that which is to come; for faith there generally conceived, apprehendeth both things eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and temporall, as before I have ſhewed: but if by faith here you meane that ſpeciall <hi>one faith,</hi> which juſtifieth to eternal ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being an apprehenſion of a thing that is eternall, and an Act of that faith, Heb. 11.1. You ſhot beſids the marke.</p>
               <p>Now whereas I uſe theſe words, <hi>Theſe 2. kindes (or ſorts) of faith are both the gift of God,</hi> I therein ſpeake but the truth, for as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, namely, <hi>Iustifying, or Eternall faith, is</hi> (as one faith) <hi>a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion given of God, for apprehending eternall life and his Adjuncts.</hi> So the ſecond, namely, <hi>temporary faith</hi> (ſo called as before I ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it) <hi>is a perſwaſion given of God, for apprehending temporary life with the Adjuncts.</hi> So that now you ſee (notwithſtanding your great ſtirre) this diſtinction being thus grounded upon the word of God, remayneth unmooveable; and I doubt not the foundation being ſo firme, but that the building will alſo ſtand, notwithſtanding all the ſtormes and tempeſts that beate againſt it; For <hi>Sola veritas invicta opprimi, ſed deprimi non potest.</hi> And I am bound to ſay, that the maine doctrines, in my writings (as by them may appeare) are warranted for truth, by authority of Scripture, and if need did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, it may be prooved warrantable by authority of approoved writers, both at home and abroad, notwithſtanding I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſlandered and derided.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:7192:43"/>
            <head>EPILOGVS.</head>
            <p>THe ground and foundation of all theſe horride reports, which are ſcatered abroad of me (good Chriſtian) concerning prayer for outward bleſſings, I here preſent to thy view; is it not <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> his collections from my writings, which hee affirmeth to be my Aſſertions, &amp;c.? Whereunto I have here directly anſwered; Iudge righteous judgement; are thoſe reports true, which thou haſt heard reported of me? Have I affirmed under my owne hand, and in my owne name, firſt, That to teach men to pray for temporall benefits, with ſubmiſſion to the will of God expreſſed, is to blaſpheme the truth? Secondly that wee may pray for any thing and have it? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Gods will muſt be ſubject to our wills, and to what wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire? Fourthly that whoſoever wanteth outward neceſſaries, have no faith, but are meere infidells, and the like fooleries? Have I either taught theſe fopperies, or are they affirmed by me in any of my writings? Who hath ever heard or ſeene it? Where doth he dwell, or what is his name? If theſe reports be but flying ſpeeches, and meere flanders, and thou canſt not produce any to ſtand forth to juſtify againſt me, that I affirmed theſe particulars, neither that any other to ſhew it under my hand, then know (whoſoever thou art, that haſt received theſe accuſations, and againe report them) that thou haſt gone beyond thy bounds, ſeeing one of Gods Canons runneth thus: Receive not an accuſation againſt any one under 2 or 3 witneſſes. And againe; Iudge nothing before the time, 1. Cor. 4.5. Yea but (it may be) thou wilt ſay, that thoſe rumours, which thou received'ſt, and againe reportedſt, concerning me, came from <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice,</hi> and it is ſtrange if he ſhould ſpeake or write any thing, much more ſuch foule things of any one, without ſound and ſufficient warrant. Strange and lamentable it is indeed, yet how true it is, I leave it to thy godly and judicious judgement, comparing my writings with his collections. And if thou findeſt (after due examination) all theſe (as hee here affirmeth) to be my aſſertions, and that under my owne hand, then let me beare the blame for ever; but if not, then know, that the reproach I hereby ſuffer, is very great, and to me the more grievous, in regard it is brought upon me by ſuch a one as he; whom notwithſtanding I deſire, that hee would yet once ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, wherein hee hath offended. In the meane time for my part, I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7192:44"/>can take it as a glory to paſſe by offences. Howſoever to finiſh all, give me leave to add this <hi>memento</hi> by an apoſtrophe. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Norrice</hi> you know that long ſince I made you acquainted with the grounds I hold, concerning praying for temporall bleſſings, whereunto at firſt you aſſented, but not longe after you framed 5. Arguments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending thereby directly to contradict that which before you aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto; which Arguments you ſent to me, and withall deſired that if they were faulty or fayling, I would ſend you word wherein: As alſo ſet downe in writing my opinion, concerning prayer for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings, which thing (at length) I did, and ſent you (as you deſired me) in writing both an Anſwer to your Arguments, as alſo the grounds concerning the point before ſpecified, wiſhing you to ſhew what I had written to whom you would.</p>
            <p>This being done (had you well done) you ſhould have ſhewed (had you ſhewed any) my writings, and mine onely, that the Reader might have judged accordingly. In ſtead of ſo doing, you drew cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain collections, grounded upon ſnaps and ſnips of my writings, wherein ſometimes my words are corrupted, ſometimes cut off by the waſte, to the deſtroying of their ſence; ſometimes ſome clauſe of your owne thruſt in, as if it were mine, and ſometimes doctrine foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in, for which you have no ground in my writings, but indeed denyed and oppoſed in them, as in this my anſwer it doth and may appeare. And yet for all this, you are not aſhamed to ſay (I wonder at it) that in this paper you have preſented to the Readers view no more, but a view of my Aſſertions, ſet downe under my owne hand, and here you have laid your credit downe to pawne, that theſe col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of yours, doe agree with that which I have written, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by theſe words <hi>(Concordat cum originali)</hi> which you have ſubſcribed immediatly after your collections; notwithſtanding that collection immediately going before (I will be bould to ſay it, and that without an <hi>If</hi>) is a doctrine of your owne invention, and none of mine, which yet you have here fathered upon my writings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Tempora, O Mores!</hi> Let all men judge whether you have not groſly carried your ſelf in this matter, in that you have laboured by your falſe collections, to make me odious in Towne and Country If you have thus abuſed my Aſſertions, ſpread before your eyes, faire writing, what marvaill is it, though ſome prejudicall Heare give credit to your ſpeeches, and through your meanes abuſe to
<pb facs="tcp:7192:44"/>eares of many with many ſenceleſſe fopperies? If you by this your dealing, either out of malice or paſſion, have not onely rayſed ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls and foule reproaches on me, but alſo to effect your owne ends, gone about to pervert both Prieſt and people, then know that God will find it out, and that without timely repentance, publikely reproove them. God give you ſo to conſider of it, as it may never be laid to your ſoules charge.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
